环球影业制作
1978年，我去了欧洲，
第一次代表巴西
参加世界卡丁锦标赛
只是单纯的开车和比赛
没有政治因素
也与金钱无关，只是单纯而真实的比赛
我们并没有想到
卡丁车可以成为一种职业
但是，它已成为我们生活的一部分
我们都有点担心
因为来到了F1
愿上帝永远保护他
危险的速度，这是我最担心的事
我要感谢他，他是一个好儿子
今年他一直很努力，诚实
对我来说，这比任何头衔都重要
很少有人真正了解我
他们不明白当赛车手的代价
我要离开朋友和家人数千英里远
住在欧洲
这么年轻，一直处于竞争中
这一切都来之不易
重要时刻来了
艾尔顿准备第一次驾驶F1赛车
我相信这是上帝给我的机会
我已经等了很久了
而她也帮助我冷静，这很好
制作人员
------------------\N翻译\N\N插线   酱油   暮羽\N驴弟   佳佳   海绵\N插线   塞魂   风扇\NSienna   西瓜\N\N时间轴\N\N酱油  海绵  宠物喵\N\N校对\NCath   月月\N\N特效&监制\N丢丢
我就是喜欢人与机械浑然一体的感觉
I always like the combination of a man and a machine.
我想这大概就是赛车运动的精华所在
I think that's the real special quality that motor-racing in general
特别是F1
and, in particular Formula One.
人们总说  车况决定一切  不是吗
People say: "Oh, it's all about the car, isn't it?"
其实不是这样
Well, actually it's not,
赛车因素可能占50%  或稍多一点
but the car is certainly 50%, probably a bit more.
即便有75%到80%
And... even if it's 75% or 80%,
其他20%则取决于车手
the other 20%, which is represented by the driver,
至关重要  是胜负的关键
is absolutely crucial. This is what can make a difference.
而赛车本身
But the cars themselves...
不管你相信与否
You either believe this or you don't.
赛车本身极具美感
The cars themselves are beautiful things.
车身上的香烟广告虽让美丽打些折扣
They are a little 'less when they are painted as cigarette packets
我也不知道现在他们往赛车上喷些什么
or whatever they paint them now, perhaps,
但整辆赛车散发着一种美
but there is a beauty to the sense of form following function,
赛车的外形从某种程度上讲非常优美
that the form of the car is expressive in some way.
加之它们在赛道上狂奔时的那种速度
The speed they're gonna to go at when they start moving.
还有车体结构设计上的精细
And the details of the engineering
即便你不是内行
even if you are not technically literate
仍然会发现这种美
are very beautiful.
雕塑般的那种美  可以这么讲
the beautiful bit of sculpture, if you like.
这种美与冰冷机械的融合
The combination of these beautiful and inanimate machines,
还有赛车手身上带有的那种英雄色彩
and the heroic figure of the drivers,
勇气和浪漫主义的体现
the sense of courage and romance,
这样一种特性
that kind of thing
是我从小就为之着迷的原因
is what attracted me I think when I was a small boy.
我认为80年代
I think formula one of the 80s' was
是F1最为光辉的一段时期
one of the most glorious times in Formula One.
那时的赛车与现在相比  结构简单许多
The cars were almost simple, compared to what they are now.
方向盘只负责让赛车转向
the steering wheel only turn the car.
换挡手柄只负责排档
A gear lever shifts the gears.
那时  仍然是赛手主宰着比赛
It was a time when drivers still made the difference
工程师和电子技师的权责有限
and all the engineering expertise and electronics
车手发挥的余地很大
still left a great deal for the drivers to do.
那时候有  "教授"阿兰·普罗斯特
You had Alain Prost, known as "The Professor"
一位驾风非常细腻精确的赛车手
a very smooth, a very calculatiing driver.
有巴西的尼尔森·皮盖特
You had Nelson Piquet, who was Brazilian,
一位充满激情而略显狡猾的车手
a very emotional, clever and cunning driver.
奈杰尔·曼赛尔  人称"英伦雄狮"
You have Nigel Mansell, who was sort of the British Lion
是一位驾风剽悍  极富观赏性的赛手
who was very exciting to watch, a spectacular driver.
当然还有一身正气的塞纳
And then you have Senna, the virtuous.
这些车手的职业生涯
And to see these drivers competing with each other,
多多少少有些重叠
more or less the same stage of their career,
欣赏他们的巅峰较量
overlapping slightly in a way,
简直是太棒了
but really at that peak together was phenomenal.
1984年  摩纳哥
埃尔顿  这是一座美丽的城市
Ayrton, this is a beautiful city,
有着美丽的街道供人漫步
with wonderful streets to walk,
但是否适合赛车比赛呢
but unsuitable to host a race, no?
的确  我最后才赶到
Indeed. I arrived at the last minute
我惊讶了  我从未到过摩纳哥
and I was surprised. I've never been to Monaco.
我进行了一些试车
I did some test drive.
很幸运  我适应了赛道
And fortunately, I managed to adapt to the path.
这里不容任何失误
There is no margin for error:
任何错误都会导致事故
any error would result in an accident.
不过目前我还是很满意的
But for now, I'm satisfied.
声音来自
雷吉纳尔多·列明\N巴西环球电视评论员
当埃尔顿·塞纳加入托勒曼车队时
when Ayrton began to be noticed aboard a Toleman.
托勒曼车队并不是有竞争力的车队
The Toleman was not a winning team.
赛车性能低下
The car was bad
从未赢下过一场大奖赛
and never won a race.
因此埃尔顿在摩纳哥的表现堪称天才
That's why what Ayrton did in Monaco was true genius.
现在很多车手都陷入一种困境
Now lots of drivers do that.
加入一支小车队
Joining a small team
然后就此销声匿迹了
and disappear without a trace.
他们的水平被车队所限制
They perform to the level of the team.
然而就有这样一类稀有的车手
But there is a rare breed of drivers,
塞纳便是其中之一
Senna was absolutely one,
他们能从加入一支小车队为起点
who can go in a small team
打破赛车性能的限制  发挥出超凡的水平
and perform so far above the perceived level of the car.
令所有人关注  不理解他是如何做到的
that everybody turns around and thinks how did he do that.
他所做到的
What he had done
令工作区的每一个人
make everybody in the paddock
都认识到他的能力
aware of what he could do,
记住他的名字  了解他的潜力
who he was and what his potential was.
他开着一辆性能低下的赛车
That he could take this car which had nothing,
却能跑出骄人的成绩
and deliver a result like that,
而且是在最为糟糕的比赛条件下
in the worst possible conditions for a racing driver.
你永远不能想象
It is impossible to overestimate
在雨中赛车有多么的恐怖  有多难
how frightening it is race in the rain, how difficult it is.
车手在雨中什么也看不见
Racing drivers can't see anything in the rains,
尤其是跟在别的车后面时
especially if they are behind another car,
硕大的轮胎卷起的层层水雾
with the big tires they have now that throw up so much spray
给你的感觉就像在大雾中驾车
that is like driving in thick, thick fog.
试想  在跑道上
You know, like trying to drive on the motorway
大雾弥漫
in thick fog,
能见度只有十几米  还要高速前进
with a 20-yard visibility at racing speed.
能做到这点是非常出众的
And to be able to that really sorts out
凭这一点  就可区分伟大车手跟优秀车手
the great racing drivers from the pretty good ones.
1984年6月3日  摩纳哥大奖赛
塞纳的第8场F1大奖赛
阿兰·普罗斯特发车很好
Alain Prost, who started well,
一车当先
has got away in the lead.
奈杰尔·曼赛尔  两辆法拉利分列三四
Nigel Mansell, the two Ferraris third and forth.
尼基·劳达列第五
Niki Lauda is in fifth position.
罗斯伯格第六
Sixth is Rosberg.
第七是曼弗雷德·温克霍克
Seventh, Manfred Winkelhock.
埃尔顿·塞纳位列第八
Eighth, Ayrton Senna.
不过塞纳一路追赶
But Senna has come up throught the field.
他从第十三位发车  已经追至第七
He started in thirteenth place and is now seventh.
奈杰尔·曼赛尔的赛车失去了控制
Nigel Mansell loses control!
埃尔顿·塞纳已超过科科·罗斯伯格升至第三
Ayrton Senna has now passed Keke Rosberg and is in third place.
又超过了尼基·劳达
It also outperforms Niki Lauda!
埃尔顿·塞纳升到了第二位
Ayrton Senna earns second place
通过赛道最危险的地段
the most dangerous part of the track!
声音来自
詹姆斯·亨特\N1976年F1年度总冠军
塞纳太出类拔萃了
a truly outstanding talent.
他每个单圈都要比阿兰·普罗斯特快3秒
He is catching Alain Prost something like three seconds per lap.
这种表现太令人吃惊了
and that is a pretty staggering performance.
普罗斯特在向裁判挥手
Prost is waving his hand to the officials.
他想要终止比赛
He wants to stop the race.
谁又能说他什么呢
Who can blame him?
从公平公正的角度来讲
In fact, from a purist and dispassionate point of view,
没必要终止比赛
there is no reason to stop the race.
裁判在我身前挥动着红旗
There is an official in front of me with a red flag.
他们想要终止比赛
They want to stop running.
而黑白方格旗也在挥动
and the checkered flag is going out.
难以置信
Incredible!
普罗斯特停在了终点前  塞纳冲了过去
Prost is stopping and Senna cross the finish line before him.
埃尔顿挥舞着手臂难掩激动
Ayrton raises his arms and gesturing with enthusiasm!
宛如获胜一般庆祝着
Celebrated as if he won the race!
如果再多跑几圈
If he had a few more laps,
胜利就非他莫属
would certainly come into his head.
我曾很有机会取胜
I had a serious chance of winning.
但在他率先冲过终点前
But until he crossed the finish line in first position,
一切都是未知的
you do not know.
F1与政治和金钱密不可分
Formula One is politics, money
当你并不那么重要的时候
and when you are not yet important,
你要会知道怎么与这些东西打交道
must also deal with such things.
当阿兰·普罗斯特  一位世界冠军
You have Alain Prost, the world champion,
在摩纳哥大奖赛上一路领先
out there leading the Monaco Grand Prix,
在湿滑的赛道上披荆斩棘
surviving all those wet corners,
跑了这么多圈
going by many recs,
渴望着在摩纳哥取得一场胜利
driving his heart out for a victory of Monaco
突然斜刺里杀出一个一年级新秀
and here comes a first year Formula One driver,
从巴西来的愣头青  埃尔顿·塞纳
from someplace in Brazil, Arydon Senna.
这是我经历过的最湿滑的比赛之一
This was one of the wetest races I've ever been at
比赛的确需要终止
and it needed to be stopped.
而塞纳无法看透的是
What Senna could not get was that
这是一场在法国周边地区举办的比赛
it was in the French area,
可以认为就是法国的赛事
considered an French event
而国际汽联的总部又设在巴黎
with the FIA being housed in Paris
又由法国人掌控着
and run by French men.
他认为  一定有除去暴雨以外的因素
To him, there has to some reason besides the rain,
并非他个人的问题
there was no problem to him,
使他与胜利失之交臂
to where they take the victory away from him
他很清楚再有三四圈
He knew in another 3 or 4 laps,
他会追上普罗斯特
he would catch Prost,
设法超过他
he would find a way around him
从而跃至第一名
and he would be in the No.1 position.
这对塞纳来说是个令人失望的结果
A tragic result for Senna. However,
不过  即使今年没有拿到世界冠军
if not the world champion this year,
如果他能继续职业生涯的话  毫无疑问
He undoubtedly will be the world champion in the future,
将成为未来的世界冠军
if his career will continue.
埃尔顿·塞纳  F1冉冉升起的新星
Ayrton Senna the new star of Formula One!
在一场激烈的比赛后
Rooms for the first time on the podium
首次登上F1的领奖台
in Formula One after a great race.
明年有什么打算
What about next year?
还会留在托勒曼车队吗
Will you stay with the Toleman team?
-你是如何打算的  -我不知道
- What are your plans for now? - I do not know.
现在还没有决定
It is still no decision,
一切都不清楚
and nothing clear.
我们还要等等看
We will have to wait more time to see what happens.
不赢得胜利
You will not be satisfied
你是不会罢休的对吧
until you are in a winning position, are you?
我相信如果你从事赛车这类竞技运动
I believe if your are doing something like competing like motor racing,
要么就出人头地  要么就江湖再见
you either do well or forget it.
我记得几周后的底特律站
I remember in Detroit, a couple of weeks later,
谣言已经在媒体间传开了
there were already rumours between media,
据说车队经理和赞助商都与他有接触
managers and sponsors looking after him.
我记得飞利浦·莫里斯公司[香烟制造商]找过他
I remember Philip Morris making a deal,
他们之后签了一个合同
a personal contract with him after that.
我们都知道他不会在托勒曼呆上三年
We knew that he wouldn't stay at Toleman for the three years,
尽管合约签了这么长
the supposed length of the contract,
因为托勒曼一直没有起色
because the Toleman team was not really improving
庙小容不下大佛
and the potential of the team is just not big enough for such a talent.
1985年
莲花车队
莲花是埃尔顿的完美选择
Lotus was a perfect team for Ayrton to move to.
这个车队曾拿下多次总冠军和分站冠军
It was a team that had won Championships and won many Grand Prix
他们在人力以及物力上提供全力支持
and they worked very very hard around Ayrton to give his talent
使埃尔顿的天分得到充分发挥
and all the facilities he needed to win.
84年  当我第一次涉足F1
When I came to Formula One in '84,
我才刚起步
I was starting.
我有许多要学要做
So I had so much learn and achieve that
任何一个好成绩都是进步
anything, any good result was a progress
对我都是动力
was a motivation.
然后我去了一个更大的车队  莲花车队
Then I changed to a bigger team, to Lotus,
我继续不断进步
and I still went up and up and up.
现在也是一样
and I'm still doing it.
即使我一时有什么问题
So even when I have some problems,
我关注的都是下一站比赛
I look always to the next race.
也许这一站我没有机会
Because maybe one race I have no chance,
但下一站  或者下五站会对我有利
but the next one or the next five will be good.
只是这一站表现不好
against one bad one.
你要做的是将胜利越攒越多
So you've got to try to make the number bigger and bigger.
塞纳的父母
并且会为之努力
and made sure to get it.
比如他在学校总是认真听讲
For example, he always paid attention in the classroom and at school,
这样他回家就不用复习
so he didn't have to study at home
就可以腾出更多时间去开卡丁车
and had more time to play with his go-kart.
声音来自
理查德·威廉姆斯\N卫报体育记者
他的家庭很富有
His family was very comfortably off.
当父母得知儿子立志成为赛车手
Once they recognised that his ambition was to be a racing driver,
他们可毫无经济压力地
they had no problem
支持儿子初期的卡丁车事业
backing his early efforts in go-karts.
但这并不代表
But it would be a great mistake to think
他的F1职业生涯就此钱途无忧
that he was able to buy his way to Formula One.
塞纳自己也意识到
Senna himself realised
如果你想在F1车坛
that in order to leave a serious
留下深刻长久的影响
lasting impact in Formula One
他必须要依靠自己的天份
he had to fight his way into it by virtue of his talent.
1985年4月21日 葡萄牙大奖赛
埃尔顿在莲花的第二个分站
声音来自
雷吉纳尔多·列明\N巴西环球电视评论员
当天气不好  赛道湿滑的时候
When the conditions were bad and the track became slippery
他的展示时间就开始了
he had something else.
埃尔顿·塞纳
葡萄牙大奖赛冠军
他在埃斯托里尔表现惊人
The race in Estoril was incredible.
只有一辆车没有被他套圈
He lapped every car but one.
感觉很好  非常棒
It is wonderful! An extraordinary feeling.
我很高兴
I am very happy because,
这是我进入F1的第二年
in my second year in Formula One,
我实现了自己第一个梦想  赢一个分站
I managed to fulfill my first dream, that is to win a Grand Prix.
这种感觉很独特
It is something unique.
它令人上瘾
It's like a drug.
给人强烈而深刻的心灵震撼
It is something so strong and so intense.
经历过一次  你就会去追寻一辈子
Once you experience it, you keep searching for it all the time.
那天雨下得很大  赛道上根本无人匹敌
It was raining really hard. There was no competition, really.
他甚至可以赢100次
He won that race 100 times.
这场胜利都对巴西至关重要
It was a race important to Brazil for many reasons,
就在那个周日
including the fact that this Sunday, Brazil,
民选总统
the elected-President
坦克雷多·内维斯过世了
President Tancredo Neves died.
这是巴西政治的重要时刻
It was a very important political moment for Brazil,
因为他是独裁时代之后
because he was the first elected president
第一个民选总统
after the end of the dictatorship.
他生了病  不久就倒下了
He felt ill and soon died.
国家可能会因此再次陷入动乱
There was the risk that Brazil would suffer another blow
这是所有人都不想看到的状况
or something like that, that nobody wanted.
塞纳的胜利因此变得十分重要
Senna's win was very important in that sense,
对公众对巴西人民对我们  都是一样
for the public and the Brazilian people and for us there,
我们是在晚上知道这件事的
and I'm sure it is realised later in the evening
我们正吃着晚餐
when we were at dinner. We went to dinner,
没多久就纷纷放下叉子回到巴西
but then left the restaurant to return to Brazil.
我是冈田米里  来自日本的电视台
I'm Mili Okada from Japan TV.
富士台  我只是电视台工作人员  不是记者
Fuji TV. I am just a TV personality and not news reporter, so...
这样啊  那我们一起拍张照片
I see. Let's make a picture together.
我想许多日本女孩
I think many Japanese girls
都是塞纳先生的车迷
are fans of Mr. Senna.
现在我就在他身边  好紧张啊
Now I am close to him and I'm so nervous...
欢迎来日本  日本见
Come and see Japan. See you in Japan.
谢谢  亲一个  再见
Thank you. A little kiss. Bye-bye.
再亲一个
Another kiss.
他是一个很全面的车手
He was very complete.
轮胎  引擎
From the tires to the engine,
车的各个部件
to every single component of the car,
他希望了解各个方面
he wanted to know everything.
他会督促每个技师工程师都发挥到极致
He was pushing every mechanics and every engineer to the very limit,
首先理解原理
to understand first of all,
然后全面提升车的性能
then to improve the overall package.
他为此花费了大量精力
And it took a lot of his energy,
和他花在驾驶上面的时间
but he was concentrated as much on that aspect of the job
一样多
as much as driving itself.
他大概是第一个和工程师技师们
He was the first one maybe to stay at the circuit
一起在赛道上呆到很晚的车手
until 9 or 10 o'clock with the engineers and mechanics.
他不愿意直接回宾馆
He did not want to go back to the hotel
或像普罗斯特那帮人一样打高尔夫
or go play golf like Prost and others.
埃尔顿的风格只能用一个字概括
There's only one word to describe Ayrton style.
"快"
That is: "Fast".
他能将赛车发挥至设计性能之上
He would take the car beyond its design capacity.
他会延迟刹车
He would break later,
飞一般地入弯  把车推到极限
flying into these corners, with the car just over the edge.
他驾驶着赛车在赛道上疯狂舞蹈
And somehow he would dance and dance with that car
却从不出轨
to where it stays on track.
声音来自
罗恩·丹尼斯\N迈凯轮车队经理
他的速度与技巧都是顶尖的
what was very apparent was his pace and dedication.
但同时  车手更需要有头脑
But in the end, what you're looking for is an intellect,
然后我想  这小伙是可塑之材
and I thought, "This guy's got what it takes."
很快他就发现
It pretty soon became apparent that
在莲花车队  发展空间太小
Lotus was not big enough for him,
那个车队当时刚刚开始衰落
that was actually a team just beginning its decline.
而他无能为力
I think when he was there really
他无法阻止这种颓势
there was nothing he could do to stop it.
车手又不设计赛车
The driver does not design the car.
所以  就像他之前做的
So he did what he had done,
像所有伟大的车手一样
he did what great drivers do,
他转会至一个更有竞争力的车队
that is to move on, to move again to a even more competitive team.
对车手来说  知道自己属于哪里
It is such an important instinct for a driver that
是个相当重要的直觉
to know where to be,
这个赛季谁比较强不重要
to know not who is competitive this season,
重要的是下赛季  谁更具竞争力
but who's gonna be competitive next season.
当时比较突出的车队
At that time the stronger teams
有威廉姆斯和迈凯轮
were Williams and McLaren.
当时的迈凯轮
The McLaren was,
我觉得和埃尔顿
I can tell, a team which has always reflected
有相似的价值观
values of Ayrton.
埃尔顿和罗恩·丹尼斯有很多共同点
In that sense Ayrton and Ron Dennis have much in common.
他们都是完美主义者
They are both perfectionists...
他们都认为
I'll use this. Both have
只要事先计划好执行好
the idea that nothing will
就一定不会出错
go wrong if it is well planned and executed
他们都努力做到尽善尽美
and have always fought for the same ideal.
罗恩是凭着奋斗
Ron comes from
走到这个位置的
a reality of hard work.
中间过程颇为辛苦
It is one that has struggled to get where he is now
但是他成功了
and has been successful.
那时他们的口号是
At that time the trilogy
"最好的车队  最好的车手  最好的赛车"
"The best team, best driver, best car"
这就是罗恩·丹尼斯领导下的迈凯轮
was led by Ron Dennis at McLaren.
80年代中叶  迈凯轮是领头羊
In the mid-80s, McLaren were the team to beat.
罗恩·丹尼斯是最佳车队经理
Ron Dennis was the best team manager.
阿兰·普罗斯特是最佳车手
Alain Prost was the best rider.
普罗斯特的绰号是"教授"
We all called Prost "The Professor"
因为他非常有条理
because he would do, methodically,
只做会让自己保持领先的事
whatever it took to be ahead on points.
如果需要他跑到第五名
If it meant coming fifth,
他会安安稳稳地去拿第五名的积分
he would hold the fifth place and collect those points
而不会为领奖台奋斗
rather than fighting for a second, third or first place finish.
而且  他极为了解赛场政治
And he certainly understood the politics of the sport,
比谁都更为精通
and he played that game smarter than anyone.
赛琳娜·斯科特
BBC电视台 沃冈脱口秀
因为你事先计划好了一切
because you plan everything out
从不多走一步
and you know where you're going.
是这样吗
Is that actually true?
我很现实
I'm very realistic,
有竞争力时我会放手一搏
so I think when I'm competitive, I know that I'm competitive.
没有的话  还是稳健一点
When I'm not, I know I'm not so.
为什么没有女性赛车手呢
Why are there no women racing drivers?
我真的不知道为什么女性
I really don't know exactly why women are not very competitive
在车坛  尤其是F1完全没有竞争力
in motor racing, especially in Formula One.
不过你知道  你很漂亮
But, you know, you are a beautiful woman,
我知道在迈凯轮
and I know somebody at McLaren
有人对你感兴趣  我可以安排的
who likes you very much, and I can arrange it.
阿兰  如果有人可以教我开车
Alain, you know, if only someone would teach me how to drive a car,
开赛车  我大概会考虑转行
a racing car, I might be able to give up this job and...
我什么都能教
There is nothing important I could not teach you.
你妻子会开车送你吗
Does your wife drive you home?
我第一次认识他
The first time I really met him
试着和他聊天是1984年
and tried to talk to him was in 1984,
我们在德国
when we were in Germany.
那是奔驰主办的活动
We were the Mercedes preeminance.
在纽伯格林有一场小比赛
We had a small race at Nurburgring
赛车是新型梅赛德斯119
with the new Mercedes 119.
有很多车手参加
There were the older rider Formula One,
现役的F1车手
not older, but some Formula One drivers
和已经退役的
plus old Formula One drivers.
我记得有丹尼·胡蒙  还有别人
I remember Denny Hulme and few other drivers.
就是这么个比赛
There was this competition
梅赛德斯的人问我
and some people from Mercedes they asked me
能不能在机场等埃尔顿
if I could wait Ayrton at the airport.
还有不到一刻钟就到了
It's about 10-15 minutes time difference
我又有车  所以我就留下来等他
and since I had the car, so I was waiting for him to bring him.
那是我们第一次交流
That was the first time we talked together
车程很长  两三个小时吧
and we had a long drive, two or three hours.
所以我们有时间说几句  他话不多
So we had time to talk. He didn't talk very much
不过我开车的速度让他很惊讶
but he looked impressed. Yes,
因为我在德国高速上开得很快
for that I was driving very fast on the motorway in Germany.
他说  你开得真快
He said, "You are driving fast."
我们谈得挺开心  关系也拉近了
It was nice and we were quite close.
那时候他谁也不认得
Because he did not know anybody.
所以第一天他总是粘在我身边
So he was always close to me during the first day.
挺有趣的
It was very funny, because
他那时候那么活泼可爱
he looked very open, very nice
然后练习赛开始了
and then we started practice
我们开始为杆位争夺
then we were fighting to each other for pole position.
他是强有力的对手
And he was very...you know, very competitive.
我拿到杆位  他是第二
I was on pole, he was second and then at the start
在比赛开始前  我自顾自骂了一句"妈的"
you know before the flag and I said to myself: "Shit."
"我得留意这个人"
"I have to take care of...take care of the guy."
那是1984年了
It was 1984.
没想到我俩会成为队友
I had no idea that we would become teammates.
在F1中  你的队友
In Formula One, your team-mate
会是最大的对手
is your biggest rivals.
就是要去击败的人
It is a person to beat
因为他是唯一一个跟你车况相同的
because it is the only one who has the car equal to yours.
我会说  迈凯轮的车比法拉利的好
I can say McLaren and that the Ferrari is better
也可以说法拉利的车更好
or be the Ferrari with the McLaren is better, but not
但不会说
that my Ferrari
我的法拉利就不同于队友的
is different from that my teammate.
因此
Thus,
尤其是在早期赛车中
especially at early career
当车手加入车队后
when a driver arrived in a team
他的第一个对手就是他的队友
and its first rival is his companion.
如果他比队友好
If it goes better than his fellow
就有机会继续前进
has a chance to move on.
如果没有  那这就是他赛车事业的终点
If not, it's the end of his career.
普罗斯特已经赢得了两届世界冠军
Prost had already won two world championships.
他在车队已经有好几个赛季
He had been there for several seasons.
已确立了他在车队中的地位
He was extremely very established in the team.
他自认为
You know he thought to himself,
以他的能力  车队会把他看作
and he thought he got the team to think of him
第一车手
as the No.1 driver,
领军人物
team leader,
会在他身上花更多心思
the guy to whom must be very devoted,
接着  塞纳加入了车队
but then Senna joint.
塞纳可不接受屈居于第二的位置
And Senna was not being to... accept No.2.
他可不是为了当配角才转会的
He hadn't...he hadn't joint the team to be the supporting cast.
迈凯轮车队媒体发布会
我们拥有世界上最优秀的两位车手
We have confident that we have the two best drivers in the world.
也是两位最专业的车手
two most professional drivers as well.
如果明年没有如往常一般赢得比赛
And if we not consistently win circle next year,
那也肯定不是车手的问题
then we certainly won't put blame on the drivers.
对我来说这是个很好的职业发展机会
It is a great opportunity for me, professional.
从个人来说
And personal point of view,
我很高兴能和阿兰共事
I am very happy to work with Alain.
在迈凯轮车队的第一年
The first year at McLaren
在埃尔顿一生中具有决定性的意义
was decisive in the life of Ayrton.
他非常紧张
He was very nervous.
就像肩负起了全世界一样
It was as if he he bore the weight of the world on his shoulders,
因为他现在需要证明
because he now had the responsibility
他是一流的车手
to demonstrate he was a first rate driver.
在塞纳来到迈凯轮之前
Before the Senna coming to McLaren
阿兰·普罗斯特被视为团队合作的克星
Alain Prost was considered the destroyer of team-mates.
我记得乔·拉米雷斯说过
I remember Jo Ramirez said,
"罗纳德  我很担心
"Ronald, I am concerned
让埃尔顿·塞纳加盟迈凯轮这事
what will happen with Ayrton Senna at McLaren.
他极具天赋
I know he has talent,
而阿兰·普罗斯特也很好强
Alain Prost has a fighter.
会制造一种敌对的气氛
Create the atmosphere of a battle
来教训一下新人
which helps him to destroy his opponents,
1986年效力于迈凯轮
与普罗斯特关系紧张
以技术来摧毁对手
Using the word "Destroy" in the technical sense.
在赛道上
Destroyed on the track,
从精神上击败对手
mentally beating his opponent.
我对乔·拉米雷斯说
I said to Jo Ramirez:
"乔  这对塞纳没用
"Jo, will be different with Senna.
因为他比其他
Because he has more talent
队上的车手
the other drivers
都更有天赋"
who was on the team."
事实就是这样
And that's what happened.
阿兰·普罗斯特都被震惊了
Alain Prost was surprised.
尽管普罗斯特对比赛的理解独到
Despite Prost had talents about
极具谋略  头脑冷静
understanding of race, intelligence and cold blood,
当他和埃尔顿比赛时  他也被震惊了
he was surprised when he began racing with Ayrton.
他完全没想到
He would never have thought
能有像埃尔顿这样优秀的车手
driver could be as good as Ayrton.
第一的条件
F1日本大奖赛
阿兰·普罗斯特
埃尔顿·塞纳
在埃尔顿的职业生涯中
Ayrton has, for the first time in his career,
他首次驾驶一辆足以夺冠的赛车
has a car capable of winning the Championship
他不想失去这次机会
and he does not want to let this chance, I mean, go anywhere.
那很正常  将要...
That is normal and it is going to do...
那你呢  你呢
What about you? What about you?
对我来说  有点不一样
For me it's a bit different.
所以你放手了
So you gonna let it go?
我是有点压力
I have a little bit more pressure,
我是说你让我有压力
I mean you put me more pressure.
能看到他们都在笑
You could see them smiles,
但同时  观察肢体语言
but at the same time, some slightly strange body language,
会发现二人心知肚明  关系并不融洽
say, just realized where they were and when was going to unfold.
阿兰明显感觉到他在迈凯轮的地位下降
Alain, who obviously, felt he was well nastied down at McLaren,
年轻的埃尔顿从天而降
the young Ayrton coming in,
显然威胁了自己的位置
clearly threatening his position.
两人都极具天赋  都是非常棒的车手
Both had great intellect. Both... they were very good racing drivers.
两人彼此间的竞争比
Beating each other is far more challenging
跟其他车手竞争更具挑战性
than beating the rest of the field.
他有个目标
He had a target.
在他加入F1之际  就众所周知
That is obvious that when he arrived in Formula One.
他的目标就是我
And his target was myself.
我还在F1时  就是大家的目标
When I rivaling in Formula One, I was the one to beat down.
我们是不同类型的顶级车手
We are very different top drivers.
我从没有过
I've never had a target,
以某个人为目标  想着"我就要击败他"
anybody, any drivers that "I want to beat him! I want to..."
我对所有车手都有着最高的敬意
I had the utmost respect for the all drivers.
埃尔顿则不同  他真的想要击败我
For Ayrton was different. He really wanted to beat me.
他想击败我成为冠军
He wanted to be the champion and beat me.
这是他的动力来源
And this was his strength.
这种行为值得赞许
That was applause in his approach
因为作为一个车手
because when you are a racing driver,
你需要动力
you want to a motivation.
摩纳哥大奖赛
1988年5月1日
1  塞纳
2  普罗斯特  +55.114"
那天  我突然意识到
That day, I suddenly realized
我不再是刻意地驾驶
I was no longer driving consciously.
世界对我来说都不一样了
It was different dimension for me.
整条赛道就像条通道
The circuit for me was a tunnel
我只需要前进  前进  再前进
which I was just going going going.
我意识到  一切已超出了常识的范围
And I realize that I was a well beyond my conscious understanding.
埃尔顿遥遥领先
Ayrton was multiple seconds into the leads
比赛完全在他掌控之中
ahead the race in hand.
在比赛还有很多圈时
With a hand full of laps to go,
车队人员告诉他
and he received a radio message for said,
你的优势很大  可以慢点
"You are so far in lead, slow down".
埃尔顿·塞纳撞上墙了
Ayrton Senna has hit the wall.
塞纳撞上了护栏  从车里出来
Senna is in the barrier! It came out of the car...
埃尔顿·塞纳正从车里出来  退赛了
Ayrton Senna is out of the car, out of this race.
埃尔顿·塞纳痛失摩纳哥大奖赛
Ayrton Senna is out of his lead of the Monaco Grand Prix.
令人难以置信
Absolutely incredible!
阿兰·普罗斯特赢得1988年摩纳哥大奖赛冠军
声音来自
阿兰·普罗斯特
他想向人们证明  比我强比我好
He wanted to show people that he was much stronger, much better.
这就是他的缺点
That was his weakness.
他车祸后的反应是
His post accident emotion
对自己异常地生气
was pure anger with himself.
他完全不能接受这个结果
He could not cope with it at all.
他甚至是走回家的
He actually walked back to his apartment
两三个小时后才出现
and it was two or three hours before he surfaced.
周末的时候  我本表现得近乎完美
I just came so close perfectly that weekend
以至于我放松了
that I am relaxed
让失误有机可趁
I open windows for mistakes.
我从中学到了教训
And I learned from that.
从那以后
And since then,
我要慢慢恢复一下  因为我有点失去信心
I progress to come back because I lost some confidence in myself.
逐步地  我恢复了
Progressly, I fight back.
那场事故之后  我变得更强
I've got much stronger, after that incident.
那一次  我似乎感受到了神
Somehow, I got closer to God.
对我来说  这是个很重要的启示
And that has been very important for me as a man.
摩纳哥成为1988年赛季的转折点
Monaco marked a turning point in the season of 1988.
埃尔顿开得异常好
Ayrton went on an amazing run,
赢得了接下来8场比赛中的6场
winning six of the next eight races
甚至在积分上领先于普罗斯特
and putting him just ahead of Prost' Championship.
你俩现在怎么样
What happens now, you two?
从现在开始  享受比赛的乐趣
We'll have good fun. We'll have good fun from now.
要竞争  也许比赛前就要开始
We will fight. Maybe fight outside the car.
冠军的竞争越来越激烈
I think it's more and more exciting to be the Championship.
不能同分一起拿冠军吗
Is it possible to be equal, the championship?
-没有  -去你的
- No. - Shit.
只能有一位冠军
Can be only one winner.
日本大奖赛
1988年10月30日
这是本赛季最重要的一场比赛
It is the Grand Prix of the season.
已经是晚上了  巴西依旧在等待
It is late at night and Brazil is waiting
埃尔顿·塞纳赢得了自己首个F1世界冠军
Ayrton Senna wins his first world title in Formula One,
实现了他孩童时代的梦想
realising a dream who as a child.
声音来自
皮埃尔·凡·弗利特\N法国TF1电视台评论员
箭在弦上不得不发
He was on board.
如果他赢得那场比赛  就是世界冠军
He was going to be the world champion, if he won that race.
所以他的压力非常大
So the pressure was huge.
马上就要出发  预备  绿灯亮起
They are about to leave. Here we are. Green light.
塞纳起步失误了
Senna will not start!
塞纳还在起跑线
Senna remains on the grid!
塞纳落在后面时  普罗斯特抽头第一
Prost came out on top while Ayrton Senna left behind.
埃尔顿·塞纳现在十四位
Ayrton Senna is in 14th place.
声音来自
雷吉纳尔多·列明\N巴西环球电视评论员
没戏了
"It's over."
他上升到第八  塞纳真是出人意料
He won the eighth place. An amazing comeback for Senna.
然后出现了他最擅长的赛况
Then there was his favourite position:
下雨了
it rained.
塞纳现在是第四
Senna is now in fourth position.
塞纳不停地超越
Senna runs, runs, runs!
塞纳已经接近了  他要尝试超越
Senna is approaching. He is gonna challenging for the lead.
塞纳和普罗斯特的大对决开始了
Ayrton Senna over Prost launches.
埃尔顿·塞纳领先了
Ayrton Senna has got the lead.
最后一圈时  我非常高兴
I started to be happy during the last lap.
感谢上帝
I thanked God.
难以置信  我赢了
It was incredible. I was going to win the championship,
尽管我又焦虑又紧张
despite all the anxiety and tension.
我感觉到了主的存在
I felt his presence.
我看见了上帝
I have seen God.
对我来说  这一刻太特殊了
It was a very special moment for me.
不能用语言形容我的感觉
An indescribable feeling.
永生难忘
I remained in the memory. It's a part of me.
巴西人 埃尔顿·塞纳
The Brazilian Ayrton Senna!
1988年的总冠军诞生了
World Champion 1988!
圣保罗
多了不起的比赛啊
What incredible race!
了不起的胜利  从第16位追上来
A great victory. He had to come from 16th place.
埃尔顿·塞纳
1988年车手总冠军
埃尔顿  作为冠军有什么感想
Ayrton, do you feel as World Champion?
我感觉很平静
I feel so much peace.
就像是从巨大压力中
It is as if someone had removed a huge burden
得到了释放
from the shoulders and head.
很难说清楚世界冠军意味着什么
It is difficult to understand what it means be a world champion.
对于说自己见到上帝的人
What do you say about the man
你能说什么
who says they had seen God in any circumstances,
更别提是在大奖赛的最后一圈了
never mind the last lap of the Grand Prix,
离赢得世界冠军仅一步之遥
you know, a few yards away from winning the world championship?
大多数人都会质疑他的说法
Most people would be skeptical.
我也不太相信
And I think most people would be right.
塞纳却坚决相信
Senna did seem to be absolutely convinced
他见到过上帝  他没有说上帝是什么
that he'd seen God. He didn't say what God was,
如何在那个时刻出现在他面前
how God appeared to him in that moment,
但信仰自由是他的权利
but he's right to say that.
他一定清楚这么说会冒风险
He must have known that he would risk, looking...
即使不会被当作傻瓜  也肯定会遭致怀疑
not looking a fool, but attracting skepticism.
他虽然说了如此疯狂的话
And who are we to...
但这样一个在F1历史上
who are we to challenge that mania
地位无人可及的人
when anybody likes make such a claim.
我们有什么权利去批判呢
But certainly unique in the history of Grand Prix.
当你谈论上帝的时候
When you talking about the God,
首先声明我也相信上帝
first of all, I believe in God too,
但我决不会像埃尔顿那样语出惊人
but I would never use the same words that Ayrton did.
当你和其他队友
When you are in the same team doing the same business
在一个队里共事
and taking risk with the driver
共担风险时
with the teammates and,
这种说法会让你觉得很邪乎
this kind of thing does not make you very comfortable,
因为这不只是
because it is not only
相不相信上帝的问题
believing in God,
而是像
it's like
上帝赐予了我力量
using that as a strength
我永远是对的
and I've been always the right.
他相信自己永远都是对的
That mean, you're thinking that he was always right.
而这在赛道上
And in this case it
是非常危险的
could be dangerous on the track,
我总是心有不安
and that I always felt, you know, sometimes not very comfortable.
没错  在F1中有很多
Yeah, there were many cynics
愤世嫉俗者
in Formula One
他们总是怀疑
who challenged whether this was
事情是否真实可信
really, you know, with authentic and real,
怀疑塞纳的感觉和价值观
on account of what he felt and what his values were.
但你知道  我经常
But you know, I was at witness very often
能更近距离地接触他
in a more private environment,
能感觉到他真诚的信仰
and it was most definitely sincere.
我们是这么觉得的
This is how we felt.
他觉得他所信仰的上帝
He felt that he was supported by...
站在他一边
the God he believed in
我和其他人
and why on earth would I
凭什么叫他放弃信仰呢
or should anybody dissuade him from that belief?
因为他
Because he
他那强烈的信仰是如此虔诚
was specially committed and strong beliefs,
而我觉得只要是积极的  就是好的
I think they are good thing as long as they are positive ones.
薇拉·露西亚·塞西特
将巴西人光辉的形象传遍世界
and gives luster Brazil's image abroad.
和我们分享胜利的喜悦
Shares his victory with us.
我很佩服他
I admire him very much.
他无所畏惧
He is very brave.
我清楚这点
I just know this.
我们以他为荣
We are proud of him.
他是我们仅有的几项引以为豪的国宝之一
He is one of the few things that we can still be proud of.
内耶达
他说  "妈  我拿到世界冠军就退役"
He said, "Mom, I will stop when I win the world title."
我心里清楚  他说的不是真的
In my heart, I knew that was not true.
我们现在都知道
We all know that.
视频资料来自
塞纳家人
在1988年大奖赛夺冠后
After the 1988 Championship, which he won the title,
你明显能看到
you could clearly
他变了
notice that he had changed.
他成功定位了自己
He had found himself.
知道自己是谁
He had discovered who he was.
这是那次夺冠所带来的结果
It was found as a conclusion in that victory.
圣诞节发生了很多事
At Christmas, many things happen.
我们结识了新朋友
We make new friends,
就像我将给大家介绍的这位
like what I'm about to introduce.
他是我心目中1988年"感动巴西"的人物
He was part of my 1988.
埃尔顿·塞纳
Ayrton Senna.
多美妙的场面
Isn't it nice?
我要问你个问题
I have a question for you.
大家都很激动  但我更甚
We are all excited but I am more than anyone else,
因为能埃尔顿说话就像做梦一样
because it is not easy to talk to Ayrton
而他现在都成我朋友了
now who is my friend.
埃尔顿  你圣诞节想要什么
Ayrton, what do you want for Christmas?
什么样的圣诞礼物
As a Christmas present?
我可不敢直白地说我最想要的
I can not say what I want seriously.
为什么呢
Why not?
绝对会被剪辑掉的
It should be censored.
就说是开开心心吧
Let's say I just want to be happy.
你可以悄悄告诉我
Tell me through my ear.
新年快乐
Happy New Year.
1990年快乐
Happy 1990.
91年快乐
Good '91.
92年快乐
Happy '92.
93年快乐
Happy '93.
1989赛季的队伍
1989 season was somewhat less harmonious
没有上一赛季和谐
than the year before.
两位车手都
Both drivers took on
不同程度铆上了劲
different levels of aggression,
尤其当他们同场竞技时
especially when racing with each other.
很奇怪的是
It is curious
英语中  "同队伙伴"变成了"队友"
that the term "team mate" is translated to "teammate."
我经常会用"队伍中的敌人"一词
I've often used the word "Enemy team".
若你同时拥有普罗斯特和埃尔顿
If you have two drivers, as in the case
这样两个车手
Prost and Ayrton,
做队"友"
as team-mates,
队内冲突
it will inevitably arise
将会不可避免
internal strife.
作为一个记者并参加过
As a journalist and someone who was in
电视制片会议的人
a TV production meeting,
每逢周末我们都会讨论发生的大事
every weekend we talked about what's the story.
我们喜欢竞争
We loved the rivalry.
不论是在赛道上
We loved it on the track in the garage
车库里还是回到旅馆之后
and in the motor home afterwards.
罗恩很挺埃尔顿
Ron was really behind Ayrton.
这点我很快发现了
But... I understood that very quickly.
但对他来说这只是生意
It is a business. For him it is business,
我一直明白这个道理
and I always understood.
当我和尼基在一起时
When I was with Niki,
开始时  他还是平等对待
it was really, half and half, I would tell from the beginning
但之后他明显地偏向我
and then suddenly went obviously behind me,
因为我更有前途
because I was the new generation.
而埃尔顿也一样  比我更有发展前途
And Ayrton was, when I was with him, the new generation.
在迈凯轮车队
You know, throghout there,
对于两个车手
peers McLaren
我总是一视同仁
I always had equality.
有时候为了平等
We would gather some points to
我们做得非常极端
quite extreme length.
例如引擎的选择
I mean the engine choice for example,
一旦我们决定
once we are determined
哪两个引擎将被用于比赛
which two engines we are gonna be use for the race,
之后就用抓阄的方式来分配
then it would be bit for the so-called number out of a hat routine.
把两个引擎的号码放在某个容器中
We put the two engine numbers in some sort of container,
然后车手们来轮流抽
then the drivers would alternate.
应该说
This was, probably
这样是为了打消某些人的偏见
this was trying to eliminate the views that
他们认为本田公司在幕后操控引擎的分配
Honda was selecting which engine went to him.
会这么想的人
But it was,
有点想多了  因为引擎决定不了一切
you know, a degree of paranoia, because it didn't do much.
不是说一个更好的引擎或更好的配置
A slightly better engine or a slightly better set up
就决定谁赢得比赛
that would determine who won the race
谁获得世界冠军
and he would become world champion.
每当比赛进行到同队的
When it ends with Prost versus Senna
普罗斯特和塞纳角逐冠军时
in the same team,
浪漫主义者会支持塞纳
you know the romantics would certainly go with Senna
而实用主义者则追捧普罗斯特
and the pragmatists would go with Prost.
塞纳的说法也许过于直白
And Senna could be a bit cruel about it,
但事实确实如此
but there were some truth
普罗斯特是个爱抱怨的人
Prost, you know, was one of those who made excuses quite a lot,
而没人喜欢听到车手找借口
which you never like to hear from racing drivers.
让人很不屑
You know, they just fester up.
车子不够好  我今天不够快
"The car was not good enough," "I was not quick enough for the day"
有时候事情就这么发生了
you know, "that's the way things go sometimes,"
普罗斯特总喜欢说车子不够好
But Prost tends to go into the munition
或者比赛时运气不好
where the car wasn't good enough or things was against him.
尽管
You know, it was,
他说的很多理由
even though every element of the explanation
也许是真的
might have much truth in it,
但找借口的行为很不讨喜
somehow it's unattractive.
你是肯定不想听的
You don't want to hear it actually.
就这样队内的矛盾开始形成
That's when the glower come of within the team.
两人的工程师开始彼此保密
That's when engineers stopped sharing information.
就这样两人开始相互戒备
That's when drivers stopped looking over their shoulders to see
斤斤计较
who is getting what from whom.
埃尔顿直来直去的个性
And Ayrton is who loved the truth,
和阿兰·普罗斯特渐行渐远
wasn't as in tune as Alain Prost
因为普罗斯特认为比赛和政治密不可分
who was adding another dimension: the politics of sport.
塞纳  普罗斯特  普罗斯特  塞纳
Senna, Prost. Prost, Senna.
开始时  他们是好朋友
At the start, they are good friends.
但现在他们之间起了战争
But now war is among.
对于法国车手阿兰·普罗斯特来说
For the French driver Alain Prost,
他的队友没有公平对待他
his teammate is not fair to him
这种不和带来的影响
and these disagreements could affect
持续了一个赛季
the rest of the season.
一个个大奖赛后他们间的矛盾越来越深
Grand Prix after Grand Prix they went more and more distant.
埃尔顿说  这个法国人很倔
Ayrton said: "This Frenchman is tough."
他想要开战
"He wants war."
不久之后
Some time later,
他们见面也不说话了
they started to not talk anymore.
声音来自
皮埃尔·凡·弗利特\N法国TF1电视台评论员
法国人让·马利·巴莱斯特
Jean-Marie Balestre,
支持的是阿兰  因为他们是好朋友
would support Alain, because they were good friends.
我记得塞纳错失摩纳哥的冠军那年
I remember Jean-Marie Balestre was the man in charge
正是让·马利·巴莱斯特当权
when Senna was denied the chance to win the Monaco Grand Prix
当时塞纳在托勒曼车队  初出茅庐
with the Toleman, when he was a novice in Formula One.
巴莱斯特是个很专权的人物  喜欢冒犯人
And Balestre was a very divisive figure, very confrontational,
喜欢争论  非常专横
argumentative and autocratic, very autocratic.
巴莱斯特
And Balestre was in charge in the,
从80年代后期
still in charge in the late 80s
到90年代初期都是汽联主席
right through the beginning of '90s,
当普罗斯特和塞纳在铃鹿赛道
when Prost and Senna had
发生那起著名碰撞时
that famous collision at Suzuka.
巴莱斯特想要处罚塞纳
and Balestre was the man who attempted to sanction,
要让他停赛
suspend, or whatever, Senna,
塞纳因此认为自己被区别对待
who felt that he was being discriminated against,
也许确实如此吧
probably with some justification.
巴莱斯特先生的房间在我的对面
Mr. Balestre had the room beside me, also on the other side,
我回来时看到巴莱斯特
and I enter into the room and Balestre is there,
然后我们进我房间里寒暄了一番
and we came into my room and we had a talk.
别忘了
Do not forget that
我和
I had a very
巴莱斯特主席
intense collaboration with
就赛车安全达成过强烈的共识
President Balestre for the safety.
但埃尔顿
But Ayrton
却一口咬定
was convinced
这是个阴谋
that it was a conspiracion
事情便一发不可收拾
and the story started like this.
我对此深感抱歉
And I am very sorry about that.
让我们欢迎FISA主席巴莱斯特先生
I would like to welcome the President FISA, Mr. Balestre.
先生们好
Please, gentlemen.
世界上所有的司机
All drivers in the world
都在电视上看着你们
are looking at you in the TV
因为他们傻傻地
because they think, stupidly,
以你们为榜样
that you are an example.
这是个很大的错误  但他们就是这么想
It is a big mistaken, but they think like that.
我重复一遍
I repeat.
今年的大奖赛最后几站不许出事故
No danger for the end of World Championship this year.
我说清楚了
State clear.
现在看你们的行动
Now depends on you.
后面比赛对我来说很轻松
And for me, the rest was very simple.
很明显  我更快
It was very very clear that I was quicker.
不管你信不信
And believe me or not,
那比赛就是场玩票
but I was playing within this race.
我速度非常快
I was -- I was very, very fast.
我知道正常情况下他不可能完成超车
I knew that he normally could not overtake.
但在日本大奖赛两三站前
But I said to Ron and Ayrton,
我跟罗恩和埃尔顿说
two or three races before Suzuka
因为每次埃尔顿想超越我时
because every time Ayrton tried,
尤其是在起步时
especially at the start, to overtake me
我都让他过去了  因为我不想出事
I opened the door, because I did not want to have the crash.
我就跟他们说
I would say to them:
从现在起  我绝不再让他了
"From now, I mean, no way I'll open the door any more.
我们各自为战
"We're fighting as a... you know,
别理会什么团队精神
don't take care about the team spirit.
我是为自己而战
"I-I-I fight for myself."
声音来自
约翰·比西尼亚诺\NESPN评论员
塞纳必须赢得日本大奖赛
Senna has to win the Japanese Grand Prix
才能让积分不会拉大到毫无希望
to keep the points battle going on to the last race.
普罗斯特知道塞纳没有放弃
Prost knows that Senna does not finish.
而他也不会对冠军放手
He will be the Formula 1 Champion.
日本大奖赛
1989年10月22日
埃尔顿·塞纳车载摄像机
普罗斯特第一  塞纳第二
Prost, first. Senna, second.
普罗斯特一跃领先
Prost jumped into the lead.
他的起跑更加出色
His start was better.
45/53
Casino之字弯
46/53
塞纳的良机来啦  他发起攻击
Here is an opportunity waiting Senna. Try to pass.
老天  太不可思议啦
Hell! My goodness. This is fantastic.
他们相撞了  这对普罗斯特有利
Finally they clash! It goes in the favour of Prost.
若比赛以此结果结束
If the race ended like that,
则普罗斯特赢得总冠军
Prost won the title.
但对于埃尔顿·塞纳来说
But, for Ayrton Senna
绝对是个坏消息
it is not a victory instead.
对于塞纳的支持者
It is difficult to-to-to many people
很难让他们相信
when you are a pro of Senna,
怎么说呢
say that, that's,
我说"我不是故意的"  他们不会信
when you say "Ok, I did not do it on purpose."
坦白讲  我不是很在意  因为
To be honest, I do not care so much, because
我发誓我不是故意的
I promise I did not do it on purpose.
但在这个弯角
But I did not open the door,
我绝没有让着他  不然事情就另当别论
which is very, very different, especially in this corner.
但如果你不是个赛车手
But if you're not a racing driver,
若你不了解赛道
in this corner, knowing the tracker,
不了解这个之字弯
knowing the chicane,
你无从评判
you can not judge.
解释这种情况是在浪费时间
It's a waste of time to try to explain the situation.
我是这样认为的
It is my-my opinion.
这是场赛车突发事故
It's a -- it's a racing incident,
尤其是在冠军争夺赛上
especially when you're fighting for the championship.
如果我想让他
Knowing that if I wanted to open the door,
那我自己就过不了弯
I could not make the chicane myself.
两人之间的激烈争夺
It was a little bit less than not yielding
互不相让
the level of aggression
虽造成了碰撞
and that caused cars to collide,
但却是赛车不可或缺的元素
which was, let's say, motor racing.
真正的错误
But really it was then what unfolded
是之后事态的发展
which was just so wrong.
南尼尼过去了
Nannini passes.
南尼尼暂时领先
Nannini is now in the lead.
塞纳还在维修区
Senna is still in the pits.
塞纳重返赛道
Senna is back on track,
但他远远落后于南尼尼
but he is far behind Nannini.
要赶超几乎不可能
Catching him will be almost impossible.
成败在此一举  只剩五圈了
It's all or nothing, five laps to go.
如果塞纳还不放弃
It will be a suicidal race for Senna,
势必要放手一搏
if he decides to try anything.
普罗斯特看到埃尔顿重返赛道
Then Prost saw Ayrton return to the race
立刻前往赛务办公室
and immediately went to the stewards' office.
南尼尼第一  塞纳第二
Nannini, first. Senna, second.
塞纳试图超越南尼尼
Senna tries to pass Nannini!
塞纳领先了
Senna is in the lead.
51/53
Casino连续弯
巴西国旗在挥舞
Brazilian flags waving!
观众一跃而起
The crowd are on their feet!
埃尔顿·塞纳
Ayrton Senna.
到达终点了
Checkered flag!
塞纳在驾驶舱里兴奋不已
Senna celebrates in the cockpit.
他拍打着头盔
He hits his helmet.
来自巴西的埃尔顿·塞纳
Ayrton Senna of Brazil!
他明显情绪激动
Visibly moved,
他推起面盔  擦拭泪水
he raises his visor and wipes away a tear.
真是场绝妙的胜利
It is a fantastic victory.
以前我从未见过此种情况
I have never seen anything like it.
我回到维修站
I went back to the pits.
看到埃尔顿在工作人员的帮助下
And I saw Ayrton, I mean, pushed by the marshals,
重新点着了引擎
and, and started again.
显然  我的心情很不好
And obviously, obviously I was not that happy,
然后我走进车库
And-and that's it. I went into the garage.
和罗恩起了争执  很压抑
I had a depressed argument with Ron.
事情就是这样
And-and that's it.
是的  不是  我不是故意
Yeah. No... I didn't mean to...
你是先去了指挥台还是车库
Did you go to the control tower or to the garage first?
车库  或许不是
Garage. Or no.
我确信你先去了塔台
I believe you went to the tower first.
可能是去了塔台吧  对的
Maybe, maybe to the tower. Yeah.
或许你和罗恩是在塔台起的争执
Maybe your argument with Ron was in the tower.
在塔台里  不错
In the tower, yeah,
因为那时罗恩已经在塔台里了
because Ron was already, was already in the tower,
在那里我们争执得很激烈
and we had the strong argument there.
但是...  无论如何
But it never, in no situation,
在塔台里时
I was, for example, in the tower
我绝没与巴莱斯特先生独处过
with Mr. Balestre, alone, for example.
根本没这种事  却有许多这样的报道
It did not happen. I read that many many times.
我们的确有过争执  有过...
We had an argument, and we had a...
我甚至没有进过赛控中心
I even not entered into the race control centre.
可能还得等二十分钟
Maybe in 20 minutes.
搞毛啊
Fuck you now.
来杯茶吗
Have a cup of tea?
声音来自
雷吉纳尔多·列明\N巴西环球电视评论员
奈杰尔  他切过了之字弯
Nigel, Nigel, missed the chicane.
走的是避险车道
He went through the escape route.
赛事委员会办公室
随着时间的过去
As the wait was prolonged,
越来越多的人担心
the more people feared
决定失去公正性
that the decision was becoming political.
日本大奖赛专场国际汽联组委会
Team of FIA Commissioners at the Grand Prix of Japan
决议将一号赛车
is to exclude the number one car
及其车手埃尔顿·塞纳的名次
and its driver, Ayrton Senna,
从比赛结果中除名
from the final outcome of the race.
比赛结束后
After the race,
大屏幕反复重播着撞车始末
a giant screen has repeatedly shown the incident
及塞纳返回赛道的整个过程
and everything that happened Senna trying to get back on track.
重审这些画面之后
After reviewing these images,
赛委会官方得出结论
race officials have concluded
塞纳在返回赛道时
that Senna failed to use the chicane
未经由连续弯
to resume racing.
此举违反了国际汽联第56条赛规
Senna has infringed Article 56 of the FIA regulations.
你是世界冠军吗  阿兰
You are the World Champion, Alain?
似乎是的
Apparently, yes.
不是百分百确定  我清楚规定
I was not 100% sure. I know the regulation.
但你不知道委员们会如何解读
But you never know how it's going to be interpreted.
但坦白讲  我挺高兴可以离开
But to be very honest, I am quite happy to leave,
因为我觉得
because I think it's...
无法再和埃尔顿做队友了
it becomes absolutely impossible to work with Ayrton.
这是比赛的完美结局
And-and that's a good end of championship.
现在我要
What I'd like to do now
向在座的各位放映一段相关录影
is to show you some footage which I think is quite relevant
赛规规定
because we're told
不能使用避险车道重返比赛
you can not use the escape routes to rejoin the race.
避险赛道不是用来避险的
The escape routes are not for escaping through.
而是应该停下来
They are in fact for stopping in,
掉头  再返回正常赛道
turning around and going out of.
那年的结果是  不除名
It is important to remember no exclusions
不处罚  不取消资格
no penalties, no disqualifications.
这次难道就可以
And for that he is excluded
把他从日本大奖赛除名吗
from the Japanese Grand Prix?
赛规一致性在哪
Where is the consistency?
简直是大错特错
It can't be right.
这是赛车史上第一次出现
That is the first time that a team
车队和自己的车手较劲的情况
as one, appeal and request against its own driver.
说真心话  我的心情五味陈杂
You know, so I was in this kind of mood where, honestly,
虽然我很想成为世界冠军
I wanted to be World Champion,
但世事难料
but everything was possible
瞅瞅自己的车队  真的挺心寒的
and looking at your own team, you know going so far.
我不知道结果会怎样
Yeah, I didn't know what-what-what could happen.
普罗斯特非常擅长耍政治手腕
Prost was very very political.
我觉得这样说一点都不过分
I think it's probably fair to say
要知道他职业生涯中加过好几个车队
that he... you know, there were several teams during his career.
但我觉得他和其中任何一个
and I didn't think his relationship
都不是欢乐而终
with any of them ended happily.
阿兰  你说你是沿正常线路跑
Alain, you say that you took a normal racing line.
但从高空看来
I would put it to you that from the aerial pictures,
你进弯似乎提前了
it looks as you had turned in quite early.
根本不是正常的过弯路线
It wasn't a normal line at all.
我赢过39场分站和三次总冠军
I won 39 races and now three Championship.
你们觉得我会故意干出这种事情吗
Do you think that I would do something like this on purpose?
我已经转向拐角处
You know, I've already turned for the corner
可能如你所想  我是早了那么一点
maybe a little bit earlier, if you want,
但那本来就是我的弯角
but that was my corner.
上诉法院决定
The Court of Appeals declares
吊销塞纳的赛车执照半年
a six-month license suspension for Senna.
警告不仅针对埃尔顿·塞纳
A warning not only to Ayrton Senna
也针对所有赛车手
but for all the drivers,
同时处罚金十万美金
and a fine of $100,000.
即便你是世界最好的车手之一
While you are one of the best drivers in the world,
也没有权利制造愚蠢事故
you have no right cause of stupid accidents.
整件事情的处理方式
The way the whole affair has been treated
就是我要对一切负全部责任
is like I have total responsibility for everything that took place there.
一切都归咎于我
I was blamed for everything
一切错误都应惩罚我
and I was penalised for everything.
对待我就像个罪犯一样
I was treated like a criminal.
这完全让我无法接受
And this is totally unacceptable.
他们取消了他的冠军资格
They took the Championship away from him
还吊销了一阵子他的超级驾照
and they suspended his license for a period.
对我来说
To me,
这是在我15年F1报道生涯中
it was the worst use of power, political power,
看到过的最无耻的滥用职权行为
in my fifteen years on the Formula One circuits.
埃尔顿永远都不会忘记
And Ayrton would never forget it.
我知道对于普罗斯特
Alain Prost, somewhere, I know,
在他内心深处  为此感到羞耻
deep down inside, was ashamed of it.
实际上  赛规在不久后就修改了
And the rules actually changed later
新赛规中  埃尔顿的行为是合法的
to allow what Ayrton did to become legal, because of it.
那段时期  埃尔顿处于低谷状态
That was quite a profound moment for Ayrton
因为巴莱斯特的行径比普罗斯特更恶劣
because Balestre had behaved even worse than Prost.
他甚至想退出F1
He even thought about giving up Formula One racing.
我让他休息了一段时间
I let him alone for a while,
慢慢劝说他
gently persuaded him
你忠诚于自己的信念
you are true to your values;
如果你坚信自己是正确的
if you believe that your values are correct values,
那么  面对这些
then walking away from
生活中的阻挠
the dark forces that you face within life
就不应该屈服逃避
just doesn't become an option.
1990年
1990赛季  他归队了  也更成熟了
In 1990 Season, he came back wiser.
赛队氛围非常和谐
The team's harmonious.
普罗斯特离开迈凯轮  去了法拉利
Prost has gone out of McLaren for Ferrari
塞纳夺冠形势一片大好
and Senna has his perfect position to compete for the title.
所有赛车手都立志超越极限
All drivers aspire towards their limits.
我的极限与普罗斯特的不同
My limit is different from that of Prost.
事实如此
This is the reality.
他不是想办法提高自己的实力
Instead of trying to improve his own capacity,
而是攻击我  他觉得那是捷径
he found it easier to attack me.
埃尔顿的思想有点问题
Ayrton has a small problem.
他以为自己是不死之身
He thinks that he can't kill himself,
因为他信奉上帝  神神叨叨的
because he believes in God and things like that.
我觉得这对其他赛车手是很危险的
I think it is very dangerous for the other drivers.
我信仰上帝
The fact that I believe in God,
虔诚地相信主
the fact that I have faith in God,
并不是像他们认为的那样
is not to say that I am immortal.
我就是不朽之身
It does not mean that I am immune from danger,
或者我与危险无缘
as has been said.
我也和其他人一样怕受伤
I'm afraid of hurting myself just like everyone else,
尤其是驾驶F1赛车
especially driving in Formula One,
危险更是无处不在
where the threat is constant.
西班牙大奖赛
1990年9月30日
是他吗
Is that him?
是谁啊
Who is it?
当时我在维修站  练习赛被终止了
I was in the pits. The practice were stopped.
我听到大家说
I hear by different people
唐纳利出车祸了
there was an accident, was Donnelly.
似乎挺惨的  特别惨  简直是场灾难
Was bad, was too bad, was a disaster, was...
后来我决定去现场亲自看看
And I decided to go to the place, to-- to see myself.
我脑子里乱七八糟的  不过最后...
Million things went through my mind. In the end, I...
我明白我无法放弃我的激情所在
I realised I was not going to give up my passion,
即便车祸的景象还历历在目
even just having seeing what I have seen.
我必须振作起来
And I had to put myself together,
走出阴霾  走向赛车  并再跑一圈
and walk out, go to the racing car, and do it again.
甚至这次  我要做的更好
And do it again, and do it even better than before,
因为要减小车祸事件的影响
because that was the way
这是我自己的应对办法
to kind of cover that impact it had on me.
我并不准备放弃
I was just not ready to give up.
即便继续比赛让我感到害怕
As much as I was scared to continue,
我还是不会放弃我的目标和使命
I was not ready to give up my aim, my target, my objective,
我的激情  梦想及生命的意义
my passion, my dream, my life.
这是我生命的意义所在
It is my life.
埃尔顿·塞纳 以1'19.844"取得杆位
据我所知  他脱离了生命危险
As far as I hear, he is out of danger, life danger,
就这次事故来说  实属万幸
which is a lot considering the accident.
厄运既然会降临到他头上
And as it happened to him,
也会降临到我们任何人头上
it can happen to any of us.
有些事情你预料的到
There are something that you can calculate
但总会有意料之外的事情发生
but there are things which are unexpected.
那些意料之外的事是最危险的
And those unexpected things are the most dangerous ones,
就像今天发生在他身上的事
like it happened to him today.
我希望以后不要再发生这种事
I hope we don't see those things in the future.
日本大奖赛
1990年10月21日
太惊人了  这是连续第三年
Amazingly, for the third time in a row,
日本大奖赛将决定总冠军的归属
the championship hinged on the race in Japan.
但这次
But this time
若普罗斯特退赛  冠军将是埃尔顿
if Prost didn't finish, Ayrton would be champion.
早上好  先生们
Gentlemen, morning.
本次比赛全程共五十三圈
Number of laps from green light to chequered flag will be 53 laps.
车手的任何危险举动或意图
Dangerous behaviour and/or dangerous manoeuvres
都将立即接受调查
will be immediately investigated,
并有可能在一次或多次F1赛事中
and may lead to suspension of the license
被吊销超级驾照
for one or more Formula One World Championship events.
有问题吗
Any questions?
去年对埃尔顿的处理恶心得像屎一样
There was a big fuck-up last year with Ayrton.
为什么要我们重复一遍
Why do we have to repeat the same thing?
最安全的做法是
The safest thing is...
如果你错过了之字弯
if you miss the chicane,
工作人员把你拦下来
the stewards stop you.
等没有车时再让你走
If no traffic, they let you go.
如果你掉头往回走
If you have to turn around and go backwards
与另一辆车相向而行  那就太危险了
against another car, that's dangerous.
好吧
Okay.
大家都是这么想的吗
Does everybody feel that way?
-是的  -是的
- Yes. - Yes.
谢谢大家  非常感谢
Thank you, thank you very much.
我受不了了  这太荒唐了
I can't stand it. I can't stand this. It's a joke.
在去年的事故后  这种讨论
After what happened last year, it's a joke,
真是荒唐至极
this situation.
刚刚也看到了  我一句话没说
You just proved here... I said nothing,
但有人说出了他的看法
and you see somebody raising the point,
如你所见  大家也都赞成他的观点
and you see everybody agreeing.
去年对我来说糟透了
And last year was really bad for me.
对不起  我在这待不下去了
I'm sorry. I'm sorry, but I have to leave.
紧张的气息弥漫了整个围场
The story down in the pit lane and on the grid is one of tension.
世界冠军触手可及
With the World Championship up for grabs,
每个人都是极度紧张
everyone is extremely tense.
埃尔顿·塞纳在今天的车手会议上中途离开
Ayrton Senna actually walked out of the drivers' meeting today.
他认为杆位的位置应该
He thinks that the pole position should be
在起跑线的左边  而不是右边
on the left hand side of the grid, not on the right.
通常来说  如果内侧赛道干净
Normally, if the inside was clear,
那当然是内侧好
the inside for sure is better.
但这的内侧很脏  外侧更好
Because it's dirty, the outside is better.
就像匈牙利站  或是
Like Hungary, or like...
理想线路就是车手通常采用的线路
The racing line is the line where the cars most normally drive.
那是最快的线路
It's the fastest line around the track.
杆位要在理想线路上  这点尤为重要
It's really important to have the pole position on the racing line.
如果你在另一边
If you are on the opposite side
就要跑在很少被使用线路上
you are on apart of the track that is rarely used
那抓地力会减半
and has half the grip.
如果你在干净的赛道上  起跑会更好
If you have the clean circuit, you'll get away better than the dirt side
因为在内侧根本没有抓地力
because on the inside you have no traction.
我们会查看一下的
We'll have a look.
拜托了
Please.
但大会仲裁
But would the Chief Steward,
国际汽联  或者说巴莱斯特会同意吗
would the FIA, would Balestre, agree?
明天的日本大奖赛
Ayrton Senna will be
埃尔顿·塞纳将从杆位起跑
in pole position for tomorrow's Japanese Grand Prix.
普罗斯特第二位
Prost was second fastest.
声音来自
罗恩·丹尼斯\N迈凯轮车队经理
移到了脏的一侧  他感觉这不公平
moved to the dirty side of the circuit, which he felt was unjust.
巴莱斯特促成了这一举措
That decision was influenced by Balestre.
我知道是他  我们都心知肚明
I know that, we know that.
我被制度玩了好几回
I was fucked many times by the system.
我对自己说  "今天想玩我  没门"
I told myself, "Today, there's no way."
今天  得按我的规矩来
Today has to be my way.
我不管后果如何  就得按我的规矩来
I don't care what happens, it has to be my way.
塞纳全力起跑
And Senna sprints away,
但阿兰·普罗斯特领先  果然发生了
but Alain Prost takes the lead! It's happened!
塞纳试图从内侧超车
Senna is trying to go through on the inside...
发生了碰撞
And a collision.
出车祸了
Clashed.
塞纳被撞了
Senna has been hit.
阿兰·普罗斯特和埃尔顿·塞纳再次相撞
Alain Prost and Ayrton Senna have come together again,
并且双双离开赛道  难以置信
and were both off the racetrack! This is unbelievable!
如果比赛继续  那么冠军得主就已确定
If the race continues, the title would have been assigned.
我们还不知道会不会有红旗出现
We don't know yet whether we're going to see a red flag.
目前还没出红旗
We haven't seen any yet,
看来比赛会继续进行
so it looks as if the race is going to continue.
冠军争夺战落下帷幕
The Championship is over.
埃尔顿·塞纳是1990年的世界冠军
Ayrton Senna is the world champion 1990.
以这种方式揭晓世界冠军有些失望
That's a very sad way for this year's World Championship to finish.
我绕到塔楼后面
I circled around back the tower
完全处在禁区
and were standing right in an illegal place,
在维修站的入口
at the pit entrance.
埃尔顿刚刚过线进入维修站
And soon as Ayrton cross the line into the pits,
我走到墙边
I came over the wall
耳麦中一片嘈杂
and in my ear,
电视台的人就不停地对我说
all the way back, from Bristo connected they were saying,
针对这次意外和车祸提问
"Ask him about the incident, ask him about the crash.
问问他谁对谁做了什么
Ask him about who did what to whom."
你能谈谈第一圈发生的事吗  埃尔顿
Can you tell us what happened on the first lap, Ayrton?
埃尔顿·塞纳  巴西人 1990年世界冠军
结果双双出局
and we both went off.
你认为这是由于杆位在赛道上的
Do you think that's because the pole position
位置不对造成的吗  你曾抗议过
is on the wrong side of the track here? You wanted to change that.
当然是
Absolutely.
你拼了老命去抢那个杆位
You fight, you break your... to be on pole,
而他们却把你放到了另一边
and then they put you on the wrong side of the circuit.
你夺得了世界冠军  感觉如何
How do you feel about being World Champion?
总不至于很糟糕吧  不是吗
It's not a bad feeling at all, is it?
恭喜你
Congratulations.
声音来自
罗恩·丹尼斯\N迈凯轮车队经理
他显然不为自己感到骄傲
He was certainly not proud of himself.
以这种方式分出胜负
Certainly not revelling in the fact that
他当然不会欢呼雀跃
this had determined the World Championship.
本年度F1车手总冠军是
Formula One World Championship for drivers,
埃尔顿·塞纳
Ayrton Senna.
埃尔顿·塞纳  请上台领奖
Approaching the World Champion, Ayrton Senna.
他知道我紧跟着他
He knew I was right with him.
他移到内线  要进第一个弯道
He moved to the inside line, going towards the first corner.
我当时在追他  他露出了破绽
I just chased him then, and he opened the gap.
他很了解我
And knowing me like he does know,
他肯定会意识到  如果机会出现了
he must realise that if there was a gap,
我会尽力赶超他
I was gonna try to overtake him.
好吧  我再问你一个问题
Okay. Let me ask you another difficult question.
如果我列出所有的世界冠军
If I were to count back all the world champions,
他们与其他车手的碰撞次数
the number of times they had made contact with other drivers,
跟你过去的36个或48个月内
that you in the last 36 months or 48 months
撞车次数相比
have been in contact with
你撞车的次数远大于他们的总和
more other cars and drivers than they might have done in total.
我很惊讶你会这样问  斯图尔特
I find amazing for you to make such a question, Stewart,
因为你经验丰富
because you are very experienced
并且对赛车了如指掌
and you know a lot about racing,
那你就应该知道作为一名赛车手
and you should know that by being a racing driver
身处无尽的危险之中
you are under risks all the time.
身为赛车手就意味着与其他人竞争
And by being a racing driver means you are racing with other people.
如果你不再力求进取
And if you no longer go for a gap that exists,
那你算不上一名赛车手了
you're no longer a racing driver.
因为我们要竞争  力争上游
Because we are competing. We are competing to win.
我们所有人最大的动力就是获取胜利
And the main motivation to all of us is to compete for a victory.
而不是为了获得第三
It's not to come third,
第四  第五或第六  对吧
fourth, fifth or sixth, right?
但事实情况却不总是如此吧
But hasn't that always been the case?
我认为这就是本末倒置
But I think it's all irrelevant.
杰克  你的看法
All what you're saying, Jack,
真的是本末倒置
is really irrelevant.
因为在过去的三年里
Because I'm a driver that won more races than
我赢得的比赛最多
anybody over the past three years.
我是历史上
I'm a driver that has been
赢得杆位次数最多的人
on pole position more than anybody in history.
我在过去的三年内获得两次车手总冠军
And I'm a driver that won two titles in the past three years.
我真想不明白
And I don't think how...
我无法理解你为什么想颠倒黑白
I cannot comprehend how you can try to turn things around
去强调我出的事故是最多的
to say that I've been involved in more accidents than anybody
因为这并不是事实
because that is not true as well.
埃尔顿·塞纳和普罗斯特之间的竞争
The rivalry between Ayrton Senna and Prost
是我职业生涯内在整个体坛中
is the strongest I've ever seen in sports
所见过的最激烈的竞争
throughout my career.
我投身于F1超过三十八年
Over 38 years spent in Formula One,
我也曾参与过足球赛事  世界杯  奥运会
I was involved in football, World Championships, Olympic Games
以及许多其他赛事
and worked in many other areas,
但我从未见过
but I've never seen
像普罗斯特和埃尔顿之间的这种竞争
a rivalry similar to that between Prost and Ayrton.
他什么都懂
He understood everything.
有人批评埃尔顿的为人处事
There were criticisms, especially by Prost,
尤其是自普罗斯特抱怨更多
the behaviour of Ayrton as a person.
但他是个真真正正的赛车手
But he really was a pure product of car racing,
他为F1带来了一种风格
在那之前  只是卡丁车比赛的特色
until that time, particular to kart,
他不轻言放弃  力争上游
which was a very no compromise kind of approach to racing.
敢与对手短兵相接
Head to head against your rivals,
他认为赛车之间的碰撞是正常的
physical contact between the machines was okay, was fine.
在卡丁车比赛中是足够安全的
In karts was you know, safe enough.
但这种风格放到F1上就有所不同了
But bring that into-- into cars was something quite different.
比他年长的对手会感到震惊
And I think that was one of those things
我认为这是原因之一
shocked his slightly old rivals.
他们无法适应
They weren't used to that too.
他们的成长背景不同
They grown up was different,
不能与对手发生摩擦的观念
was rooted in the belief that you didn't make contact
根深蒂固
with another rival's car,
因为你可能因此而丧命
because if I did that you were like to die.
F1历史上最为伟大的两大神车手
Two of the greatest champions in the history of Formula One
共沉沙海  冠军毁于一旦
ended up in the sand. Championship ruined.
他们互相指责  但普罗斯特最为刻薄
They accused each other, but Prost was the hardest.
他的反应非常暴力
His reaction was violent.
我当时真想冲他脸上打一拳
I wanted to punch him in the face,
没能拿到冠军
but I was so disgusted
让我觉得很不爽
that did not succeed.
这让我很恶心
It makes me sick.
此后的几个赛季
Senna versus Prost,
塞纳和普罗斯特继续他们之间的争斗
which went on for a couple of seasons more,
是当时F1最大的看点所在
was just absolutely wonderful for Formula One's appear.
下面播放体育新闻  昔日战友反目成仇
The sports. It's the end of a love story.
电视的收视率上升  一切都热情高涨
The television ratings improved. Everything went up.
成为人们的热点话题
People talked about it.
人们争论不休  大为震惊的同时为之着迷
It was controversial, shocking, fascinating.
同时也造就了这项运动的风行
The success of the sport also breed in all
伯尼·埃克里斯通非常聪明
commercially and Bernie Ecclestone, he was clever
把握住电视转播权
in the way to distribute television.
但是要想保持收视神话  需要不断爆料
But, to keep the audience, you need the publicities
而普罗斯特和塞纳的故事最为红极一时
and of course, the Prost and Senna story was a big hit.
由于F1在电视上的影响力
Ayrton became very famous outside the sport,
埃尔顿声名远扬  甚至传到体育界之外
thanks to the impact of Formula One on TV.
我为这些人感到抱歉  因为
I feel sorry for the people because...
他们都是好人
They are nice people
看着他们被推开并不好受
and it is not a good way to see them being pushed away.
我非常抱歉
I...I feel so sorry.
巴西的形势大为不同
In Brazil, it was very different.
人们对当时的统治制度非常不满
The people were unhappy under their regime that was ruling then.
贫穷局势危殆
Poverty was just desperate.
他在艰难时期
So his appear there to hard time
对巴西人民产生了非凡的影响
was extraordinary.
当时巴西的局势令人沮丧
The situation in Brazil was very negative and depressing.
但埃尔顿多次获胜之后
But many times, when Ayrton won,
没有像其他人一样试图掩饰巴西国籍
instead of trying to hide his Brazilian origins, as others did,
相反  他高高挥舞祖国的国旗
he did the opposite, waving the flag of his country.
他每周日都会把国旗放入车内
He took it inside the car every Sunday.
他鼓舞了一代人
He was an inspiration to people.
因此人们非常喜爱他
That's why they loved him so much.
没有任何事情
Attending a Brazilian Grand Prix,
能和参加巴西大奖赛相比拟
there's nothing like it.
埃尔顿·塞纳也处于顶峰状态
And when Ayrton Senna is on top,
能亲身体验  进入赛场
it is just an out of body experience to be involved,
让人觉得仿佛灵魂出窍
to be in the paddock, to be on the grid.
人们问我
People ask me,
"十五年的F1赛场生涯中
"What was your greatest experience
你最为难忘的经历是哪一次"
of the fifteen years on the Formula One circuit?"
他们对我的回答感到吃惊
And they're amazed that I say,
我的回答是  "比赛第一次回到圣保罗
"The first time that the race-back went back to Sao Paulo,
回到英特拉格斯赛道"
to Interlagos."
塞纳处于杆位
Senna is on pole position
他的车开动后
He started to race
场内的三十万巴西车迷
and there're 300,000 Brazilian fans at that circuit
齐声同唱
singing
冲  冲  冲  塞纳  塞纳
"Oley, oley, oley, Senna, Senna"
引擎发动时
When the engine started,
你无法听见近在身旁的引擎声
you could not hear the engines right next to you
因为车迷们
for the sound of the fans
不断为他歌唱祈祷
singing his prays, singing with love
表达对他的伟大成就
for his accomplishments
和他这个人的热爱
and for love of the person.
他很想赢得巴西大奖赛
He wanted to win the Brazilian Grand Prix.
他想赢得自己的大奖赛
He wanted to win his own Grand Prix,
而这一次  职业生涯七年之际
and here it is, seven years into his career,
他还没赢得对他而言最有意义的比赛
and he has not won the most meaningful race.
1991年
声音来自
雷吉纳尔多·列明\N巴西环球电视评论员
埃尔顿从未赢得巴西大奖赛
Since he entered Formula One
他一直梦想着能在自己的祖国夺冠
he always dreamed of winning in his home country.
巴西大奖赛
1991年3月21日
起步很好
A good start.
加油  塞纳
Come on, Senna!
塞纳占据有利形势
Senna is in command.
54/67
埃尔顿领先
Ayrton pulled out the lead.
所处的位置让他轻而易举就能赢得比赛
He was there really, faced with a very easy nice win.
塞纳来了  开始下雨了
Here's Senna. It's starting to rain.
下雨了  它必须停
It's raining. It must stop.
然后变速箱卡住了
And then the gearbox jamed
他还剩下几圈
and he was faced with several laps to go
只能挂在六档
only having the sixth gear.
剩下七圈
7 Laps Remaining
驾驶卡在六档的F1赛车似乎是不可能的任务
It seems impossible to drive a Formula One car stuck in sixth gear.
埃尔顿想要停下来  他无法再驾驶
Ayrton wanted to stop. He could no longer drive it.
但他已经努力了多次
But he had already tried
不想前功尽弃
many times to win the Brazilian Grand Prix
体内迸发了独特的力量
and found a special force within himself.
最后一道弯  塞纳冲过终点线
The last corner. And Senna crosses the line.
夺冠
Go for the win.
埃尔顿  埃尔顿
Ayrton, Ayrton...
来自巴西的埃尔顿·塞纳
The Brazilian Ayrton Senna!
他在英特拉格斯获胜了
From end to end, he wins at Interlagos!
塞纳的伟大胜利万岁
A wonderful victory for Senna!
埃尔顿·塞纳
1991年巴西大奖赛冠军
不可能
No way!
该死
God damn it,
我赢了
I won!
普罗斯特  你个阳光沙滩
Prost, the sun of a beach!
1991年巴西大奖赛冠军
冲  冲  冲  塞纳  塞纳
"Oley, oley, oley, Senna, Senna"
他夺冠后便晕了过去
He won and then fainted.
这是他最具英雄气概的时刻
It was his most heroic moment.
由于身体的巨大压力
Because of the tremendous physical effort,
我肩部和颈部的肌肉痉挛
I had muscle spasms of my shoulder and neck.
非常痛苦
The pain was tremendous.
这周末的生理和心理压力
The physical and mental stress this weekend
前所未有
was unheard of.
但如果只能有一种结局
But could there be only one result,
献出生命我也要完成比赛
I finished the race with nothing left.
怎么了
What's wrong?
肩膀  肩膀
The shoulders, the shoulders.
只是我的肩膀
Just my shoulders.
来吧  爸爸  过来
Come on, Dad. Come here.
过来
Come here.
别碰我
Do not touch me.
别说话  埃尔顿
Quiet, Ayrton.
别碰到我
Do not touch me.
需要帮助吗
Need any help?
把国旗拿给我
Bring the flag for me.
今天  我奋力拼搏
Today, I fought hard.
我想要以第一名的成绩完成比赛
I wanted to finish the race and finish in first position,
因为伟大的上帝
because HE is the greatest
终究会保佑我赢得比赛
and HE will give me this race after all.
事情就是这样
That's what happened.
上帝保佑我赢得了比赛  我很高兴
It is God who gave me this race and I'm happy.
激动人心
It was thrilling.
向巴西人塞纳的胜利致敬  祝贺他
All hail the Brazilian Senna for his victory. Congratulations.
我感谢祖国巴西  感谢所有的车迷
I thank all of Brazil. I thank all the fans.
这周末我感到身边如此温暖
This weekend I felt so much warmth around me
我们必胜
that we could not do anything but win.
不会有任何闪失
It could not have been any other way.
我们做到了
And we did it.
圣保罗  塞纳家
在巴西生活会非常艰难
Life can be very difficult in Brazil. You have...
巴西有很多树  所有这些树木
in Brazil you have all these trees, all these trees...
有迷人的自然风光
You have fantastic nature.
你能够坐拥所有用钱能买到的好东西
You can have all the good material things that money can buy.
但同时  你面临许多问题
But at the same time, you have lots of many problems.
社会问题和贫穷  尾随而来的暴力
Social problems and poverty, some violence as a consequence.
我尽力
I try to help
为孩子们做些事情  尤其为孩子们
a little bit for children, particularly.
声音来自
维维安·塞纳\N埃尔顿的姐姐
很多人慕名而来寻求帮助
there were a lot of people asking for help
解决私人问题
for personal problems.
有时医院和慈善机构寻求他的帮助和捐助
Sometimes hospitals and charities sought his support and donations.
埃尔顿愿意捐款  希望能有所作为
Ayrton gave donations and tried to work things out.
他希望能更有效率的做好这件事
He was wanting to do this in a more organized way.
他不想一直随意地捐款
He did not want to continue making random donations.
他希望将其发展为一个整体
He wanted to develop a whole thing,
有秩序有效率地帮助巴西
something organised and structured to help Brazil,
尤其是孩子们
especially the children.
1991年的埃尔顿  状态非常棒
Ayrton, in 1991, was in great form.
我认为这是他最强的一年
I think it was his strongest year.
他赢得了七场比赛  时不时地夺得杆位
He won seven races, constantly on pole position.
紧张感一如既往
The intensity was every bit as high as ever.
但他似乎还有成长的空间
But he just seemed to be unfolded with further bit of growth.
他作为一个人的成长
He grew as a person.
墨西哥大奖赛 1991年6月14日
但之后的赛车让他备受伤害
But then the car beat him hard.
他第一次发现
For the first time, he really thought
他会被F1赛车所伤
he could be hurt in a Formula One car.
席德·沃特金斯教授  F1赛医
你感觉埃尔顿如何
How do you feel about Ayrton?
他很好  没事
He's fine. He's been OK.
-不用担心吗  -不用  不需要
- No problems to worry about? - No, no. Not at all.
和我打过交道的车手中
It's...the deepest personal relationship
我和他私交最深
I've ever had with any driver.
无论什么时候我走向赛道遇见塞纳
Whenever I got to the circuit and ran into Senna
通常他被采访或是被很多人围着
usually he was being interviewed or surrounded by people.
而他一看见我
And the moment he saw me,
脸上便会展开笑容
his face would always light up with a beautiful grim,
因为他非常谦逊
because he had that wonderful humility,
这在赛车手中并不常见
which is not common for most racing guys.
-好的  -乐意效劳
- Okay. - It was a pleasure.
小心
Be careful.
你还有很多事情要做
You still have so much to do.
是的  很多
Yes, more.
有问题吗  请说
Questions? Yes
罗兰先生
赛事总监
-弯道和边拦  -是的
- that we had with the tires. - Yes.
如果撞上轮胎
You happen to hit the tires.
很有可能你会被抛向空中
It's very likely to throw you up into the air,
最后不停地翻滚
and you end up rolling and rolling.
我在墨西哥的遭遇就是这样
That's what happened with me in Mexico,
这在其他选手身上也发生过
and that has happened here with other people.
我想这不是我们此时
I agree that for the moment
能解决的问题
it's not the ideal thing that we can cover.
主席昨天已和莫斯利先生说过
The President has talked yesterday with Mr. Mosley.
不  不  不  别管莫斯利先生
No, no, no. Forget Mr. Mosley.
-他已经...  -别管他
- And he has ... - Forget it.
好的  国际赛车联合会主席...
Okay. The president of FISA...
不  别管主席
No, forget the president.
我们来讨论塞纳先生提出的问题
We discuss the issue raised by Mr. Senna,
我们今天能为比赛做什么
what we do today for the race.
这场比赛  我们无能为力
For the race, we can not do anything.
我认为最好不要把那些轮胎放在那儿
I think it is better to not have those tires out.
昨天我碰巧在第一个之字弯错过了刹车点
I happened to lose the braking point at the first chicane yesterday.
让我说完  让我说完
Let me finish. Let me finish.
-我直冲过去  路被挡住了  -我知道
- I went straight. It was blocked. - I know that.
我没法调头
and I could not turn back.
如果我们移走轮胎  就必须换上锥形路障
If we move the tires,we must place the cones.
可以  那样的话  就有缓冲区域
Yeah, okay. In this way, there is a run-off area.
是的
Yes.
不  不
No, no.
你必须从相同的地方重新发车
You must restart from the same place.
因为你必须顾及到赛道长度
Because you must respect the distance of the race.
对不起  但这就是规定
I'm sorry, but this is the regulation.
这就是规定
This is the regulation.
这都写在规定里了
It is written in the regulation.
我们昨天收到的信
We got the letter yesterday.
第三页
Page three.
在这  最后两段
Here. The last two paragraphs.
对你来说   是个合理的惩罚
Very good penalty for you.
让·马利  也一样
Jean-Marie, is the same thing.
没问题  埃尔顿  没问题
No problem, Ayrton. No problem.
这是最好的决定  让·马利
This is the best decision to take, Jean-Marie.
正确的决定  你必须理解
The right decision to make. You must understand.
我的决定才是最好的决定
The best decision is my decision.
我对此保持怀疑
I have a feeling for that.
不  因为你不知道我的决定是什么
No, because you don't know what's my decision.
我的决定  每次  都是最好的
Is the best, at every time,my decision.
我的决定是
And my decision is
进行民主投票  只有赛车手可以投票
a democratic vote. Only the drivers.
举手表决
By hands.
谁赞成将轮胎更换为锥形路障
Who are in favour of the replacement tire by the cones?
举手
Your hand.
放下
Stop.
反对的
Against?
弃权的  大伙都同意  很好
Abstention? Everybody agrees, ok.
马上开工
Immediately, the work.
由你换下轮胎  可以吗
You replace the tires by the cones, ok?
三小时以后
阿兰  弯道上发生了什么事
Alain, what happened at the chicane?
我试图超过塞纳
I tried to overtake Senna. It was ...
他整场比赛都在阻挡我  不太好
blocked me through the race, not very correct.
我觉得普罗斯特已经臭名远扬了
I think everyone knows Prost by now.
他总是在抱怨  不是抱怨车子  轮胎
He always complain either, by the car or tires,
抱怨团队  技师  燃油或赛道上其他选手
the team, mechanics, fuel, the other drivers of the circuit.
一切都是别人的错  他永远觉得自己是对的
Always somebody else to be blame, never his fault.
好的  没问题
Yes, no problem.
我没什么放不下的  反正我得不了冠军
But I have nothing to lose. I can't win the championship,
但如果我再在赛道上看到他阻挡我
but if I find him again at the same way,
再这么做的话  我会把他的车挤出赛道
do this correctly the same way. I will push him out.
普罗斯特被法拉利解雇  因为他批评赛车
Prost was sacked from Ferrari because he criticised the car.
他目前所能做的就是休假一年
Anything that he could do  was taking a year off,
跟所有人说他去休假
telling everyone he was on sabbatical.
大奖赛中  我最喜欢是发车的时刻
My favourite part of a Grand Prix was the starting grid
我以前常会从维修站走出来
and I used to do the pit walk to,
走到起跑线的中央
walk down the centre of the grid
报道起跑线上各支队伍的最新动态
and give an updates on every team that was on the grid.
我不知道是不是因为
I do not know if it was because
其他人相比  我更接近起跑线
I was getting closer to the front of the grid
或者离发车位置更近
or closer to the start of the race
但我发誓  事实是
but I swear to you, as a fact,
当我站在埃尔顿·塞纳的赛车旁边
when I stood next to Ayrton Senna' s car.
就会有一股战栗的感觉
at the certain times , the hair will stand up on my arms.
那里有一股能量  一股力量
There was an energy, there was a force,
一股精神
There was a spirit in that cockpit.
那感觉是你在其他赛车手身上感受不到的
that you could not find there around any other cars on the grid.
让人为之振奋
It was absolutely electrifying.
日本大奖赛 1991年10月19日
如果我拿了第二  那比赛就结束了
If I finish in second place, The championship will be over.
如果曼塞尔输了
If Mansell does not win,
毫无疑问  比赛也就结束了
Then, it's almost certain that the championship will be over as well.
9/53
曼塞尔试图超越  他径直冲了出去
Mansell tries to overcome, but he goes straight on.
曼塞尔径直冲了出去
Mansell goes straight on.
比赛结束了  曼塞尔出不来了
The Championship is over. Mansell can not leave.
埃尔顿·塞纳拿到了第三个总冠军
Senna Ayrton three times world champion
巴西选手埃尔顿·塞纳  三冠王
The Brazilian Ayrton Senna, three world titles!
这位国际体育天才
A lifetime dedicated to this moment
以一生的努力换取了这一刻
by a genius of international sport.
三个世界冠军
Three-time world champion
以及无数的荣誉
and many other titles before him.
年仅31岁
And only 31 years old.
获得了33个分站冠军  三个总冠军
33 wins, three world titles.
不断刷新世界记录
Breaks record after record.
也只有塞纳才可以做到
It celebrates as only Senna can do.
塞纳的三个总冠军注定会让他名垂千史
Senna's third world title, and sures that he would be right among the old time grid.
这对我来说真是特别的礼物
It is a very special gift for me.
非常感谢
Thank you so much.
1991年11月5日  巴西  圣保罗
我跟着塞纳  和他一起散步
I followed the Senna, walked with him
我们一起在许多国家的街道上散过步
the streets of many countries around the world,
特别是到了像日本这样的赛道
especially to get to the circuits, as in Japan,
旅馆距离赛道一公里远
where there is one kilometre from the hotel
路上会路过游乐园
to the track and cross an amusement park.
我常想  怎么会有人如此受到热爱
And I thought: "How can a person be adored so much? "
可以说是到了无比崇拜的地步
It was a worship without limits.
我亲吻了塞纳
I kissed his hand next to the Senna,
这位三次世界冠军的手
three-time world champion.
我要塞纳  拥抱他  亲吻他
I want Senna. I want to hug him and kiss him.
我有一整箱他的照片和新闻报道
Got a box Photos and newspaper articles.
应有尽有
Everything you can imagine.
他是巴西唯一的优点
He is the only good thing in Brazil.
三次问鼎之后  我见到的塞纳与之前判若两人
After the third world championship I saw another Senna.
他是如此的满足  充满自信
He was very satisfied and  very confident.
他对赛车这项运动了如指掌
He knew the sport better than ever.
他看到了此项运动的优和劣
He saw with realise for the good and the bad.
他仍同围场上的新手一样热爱着赛车
and he still loved it as much as a new one in the paddock.
这假期真是太棒了
It is a wonderful holiday.
一切顺利
Anything goes.
你今天有谈到F1吗
Have you spoken to Formula One today?
F1太规矩了  今天可是狂欢节
Formula One is too rigid. Today is Carnival.
你女友是否曾对你说过"再快点  埃尔顿"
Some of your girls ever told you: "Faster, Ayrton?
是的
Yes.
埃尔顿  三个总冠军
Ayrton for the third world title
这是他在开始F1赛车前
was the culmination of a script he had written for himself
就为自己定下的计划
well before entering Formula One,
因为他知道自己能做到  并且能做得更好
because he knew he can do it and can do even more.
他早已是巴西的体育明星
He was already an idol of sport in Brazil.
在取得了三个总冠军之后
With the third title,
他成为了世界明星
he became the world.
我有一股不断完善自我的冲劲
There is a great desire on me on improving.
我很高兴自己变得更加出色
Getting better. That makes me happy.
每当我感觉自己学习的步伐慢下来
Everytime that I feel I slowing down my learning process.
遇到瓶颈期时
my learning curve is getting flatten or whatever.
我就会感到很郁闷
Then it doesn't make me very happy.
不仅是作为一名专业赛车手进步
And that a pride not only the professional,
也是作为一个人
as a racing driver, but also as a man.
当然
Of course.
和成为赛车手相比
I shall have a lot more to learn as a man
我在做人方面  还有很多要学习
than a racing driver.
因为我的职业生涯不可能持续很多年
because my career couldn't last for not many years.
但愿  我能活的更长久一些
My life, hopefully, would go for a long time.
或许我现在只走过了人生的一半
Maybe I'm only half of my life right now.
生命中依然还有很多事要做
So there is a lot to go, a lot to learn,
很多东西要学
and a lot to do still in life.
当我真正完善自己的时候
And the happiness will come,
真正的快乐就会油然而生
when I feel complete as a whole.
那种快乐与我今日的快乐不可同日而语
which differently I don't feel today.
不过  我还有大把的时间去获得这种快乐
But I have plenty of time to fulfil that, too.
1992年
下一赛季
For the next season,
比赛完全被颠覆
the level of the competition was distorted
一切归因于威廉姆斯车队使用的新技术
by what was going on technics with the Williams cars.
赛车能够自动调节平衡
The car balanced itself.
每个拐弯处都由电脑操控
Each corner was controlled by computer.
赛车手所要做的就是
What the drivers have to do is
把他的右脚踩在油门上  不断加速
put his right foot down and go as fast as possible.
因此  对于一辆无法自我平衡的赛车
So in a car without that,
这无疑是个很大的弱势
it was at serious disadvantage.
迈凯轮完全无法和威廉姆斯-雷诺比拼
McLaren is still well off the Williams-Renault's place
三届世界冠军埃尔顿·塞纳
with the result, that the three times world champion Ayrton Senna
不可能继续蝉联冠军
has no chance in retaining his title.
当你卷入这股
When you enter into this sort of
电子技术战
electronic war
你会发现自己完全处于进退两难的境地
you can find yourself completely stuck.
电子技术战的形势逼人
Electronics do a given situation.
奈杰尔·曼塞尔  1992年世界冠军
我认为这并非大家所期望的
I do not think it really what you want.
大家想要的是一名真正的
to have a throughly World Championship
车手总冠军
of drivers.
谈判很漫长
The negotiations were lengthy
谁将会成为普罗斯特的队友  仍不得而知
and still do not know who will be Prost's team-mate.
三届世界冠军已经和威廉姆斯车队
The three-time world champion has signed
签订了一份长达两年的合约
a two-year contract with Williams
本周即将开始测试
and during the week begin to test the car.
阿兰·普罗斯特
当我九月份在埃什托里尔比赛时
I realised that
我就意识到了这点
when I drove the car in September, in Estoril
前几圈  路面很湿
and the first few laps, it was wet
车子的性能简直是太棒了
and the car was absolutely unbelievable.
职业生涯中  我从未如此酣畅淋漓开过车
I have never driven a car like this in my career.
不过  那是真正的赛车
But, yeah. It was a native car
时机恰到好处  车子性能也很棒
the time was good, a good second minimum a good second quicker
我在争取和威廉姆斯车队签约
It's not a secret that I've been
这已经不是
trying very hard to get some
什么秘密了
some deals with Williams.
情况非常复杂
Situation is very complex.
情况不大好  也不明了
It is not nice. It's not clear, either.
有一件事  我确信无疑
I'm pretty sure of one thing:
如果我停赛一两年
I'm the one that has more to lose
我的损失比任何人都要惨
if I had to stop for a year or more,
因为我站在了职业生涯的顶峰
because I am at the peak of his career
F1赛车手的职业生涯是有限的
and the career of a Formula One driver is limited.
如果停赛  我的损失将比任何人都惨重
So if I stop, I'd lose out more than anyone else,
不管是在职业  还是在个人方面都是如此
at both professionally and personally.
阿德里亚娜·盖里斯图
塞纳的女友
1993年
1993年埃尔顿驾着他的赛车  如有神助
In 1993, Ayrton steered his car so brilliant.
在我看来  那是他表现最好的一个赛季
For me, it was his best season.
欧洲大奖赛  1993年
摩纳哥大奖赛  1993年
虽然大多时候
even though he spent most of his time
他都落后于威廉姆斯车队
looking at the back of Williams,
他们的车比他的快多了
which is much faster than his.
法国车手阿兰·普罗斯特
The French driver Alain Prost
第四次赢得了F1大奖赛车手总冠军
has won the World Drivers Championship Formula One for the fourth time
普罗斯特获得了冠军  准备退役了
Prost won the championship and duely retired,
从此退出了历史舞台
thus getting out of the way.
看起来你与迈凯轮即将告别
It seems like a little goodbye from you to McLaren.
你觉得这会是你在迈凯轮的最后一个赛季吗
Do you think it was your last season at McLaren?
我想是的  这将会是我的最后一个赛季
I think so. I think it to be my last season.
我有一份三年的合约
I have a three-year contract.
七月的时候
Then I have a moment where in July
我接到了弗兰克的电话  他跟我说
I have a phone call from Frank, and tells me:
我们得谈谈  雷诺方面给了我很大的压力
"I need to talk. I have a big pressure from Renault
我要和你谈谈
"And I need to talk to you about something."
我说  好了  弗兰克
I said, OK Frank.
我想我知道你要和我谈什么
I think I know what you want to talk about.
但是  我现在在休假  我要休息四五天
"But I'm on my holiday." I have four or five days on my holiday.
如果雷诺方面有话要和我谈
"If Renault's people want to talk to me,
让他们来见我
they come to see me
实际上他自己来找我了  带着这个计划
In fact he comes himself, with this plan,
跟我解释说
came to see me and tried to explain to me that
雷诺想把埃尔顿招致麾下
Renault are thinking of having Ayrton in the team
明年和我搭档
with me the year after
我说  这么做不对  我们是有合同的
I said, "OK, it is not fair. We have a contract.
在赛季之中
Even thinking about that is not fair
有这种想法都是不应该的
in the middle of the season.
先把这事放放  等等看
So let's put in this way, let's wait a little bit,
再等几场比赛  看会发生什么
a few races, and we see what happens. "
实际上  我下面要跟你说的
And in fact I'm going to tell you something
没人知道  或者只有极少数人知道
that nobody knows, or very few people know,
但现在说这些也未尝不可
but that's good to talk about that in this...
我当时不想
I did not want to...
我不想再和埃尔顿做队友了
I don't want to be a teammate with Ayrton again.
我不想让人们觉得
I did not want to continue with this perception of the people say
埃尔顿就是开着破车的小可怜
"OK, Ayrton is the poor guy with his small car and
阿兰呢  他要是赢了  很正常
Alain is... when he wins, it's normal,
因为他的车好嘛
because he has the best car. "
我就说  我明白你们想要埃尔顿
I said: "OK, you want Ayrton in and I understand very well.
但是你们得按合同
But you pay me
支付我明年的年薪  我就退役
the contract next year and I will stop. "
我不想退役
I did not want to stop.
我真的不想退役
I really did not want to stop.
但是看到事态又一次发展成了这样
But to see the situation going again,
特别是在你自己的国家
especially in your own country,
又一次重蹈覆辙
going in this direction again,
我很快就下定了决心
I took the decision myself very quickly.
但我打算过一两个月再告诉他们
But I wanted to tell them just one month or two months,
因为我想拿这个世界冠军
because I wanted to be world champion.
我不想失去这个机会
I did not want to lose this opportunity.
在我确认自己可以拿到冠军奖杯的时候
When I saw that I was going to be world champion,
我说  好吧  你们付钱  我退役
I said, "OK, you pay the contract I stop.
我受够了
I've had enough. OK? "
这就是我当时的作为  我不想退役
That's what I've done. I did not want to stop.
我退出F1就是因为这个原因
I stopped Formula One only because of that.
不然的话我还会继续的
Otherwise I wanted to continued.
埃尔顿在摩纳哥站奋尽全力
Ayrton fought hard to win at Monaco,
但还是没能夺冠
but did not make it,
想拿下铃鹿站  也没能成功
Tried to win at Suzuka, but did not make it,
当他终于进入了威廉姆斯车队
and when he struggled to go to Williams
却已经接近他生涯的终点
was the end of his career.
有时这一切都是徒劳  我们总是说
Sometimes it makes no sense ... We always say
要为理想而奋斗
that we must fight for our ideals,
为生命的意义而奋斗
for what we want out of life.
但有时风雨过后  看到的却不都是彩虹
But sometimes the battles do not bring the desired results.
1993年  澳大利亚大奖赛决赛
咱们都要尽全力
Let's try doing the best we can.
当然
Of course.
把别的事情都放到一边
OK, we'll put behind this what has happened.
当然
Sure.
就算我们得好好谈谈  也不是今天
Even if we got to say anything,
今天有今天的事情
that was my goal in there.
好  我明白
Okay, I know it.
就算我不跟你谈  即使什么也谈不成
If I'm not talking to you, if we didn't talk at all,
我也不会改变  这是我一直奋斗的目标
I wouldn't change ... that's I always tried.
你钻出赛车的时候
What did Ron Dennis say to you
罗恩·丹尼斯跟你说了些什么
when you step out from the car?
他说  现在改主意还不晚
It's never too late to change your mind.
他说他为我高兴  而且...
But anyway, he said he was happy for me and...
他跟我也是这么说的
That's what he told me, too.
罗恩就是这样
That's Ron.
我说  咱们必须记住这些美好的时光
And I said you know, we must keep the good times,
这些美好的片段  就此结束
the good moments, and let's finish that way.
以美好的回忆结束
Finish with the good things.
这是塞纳为迈凯轮车队效力的最后一站
It was Senna's last race for McLaren,
也是普罗斯特为威廉姆斯效力的最后一站
Prost's last race for Williams.
当时没有人会想到
and although nobody knew,
那是他们两人
that it was the last time
最后一次登上领奖台
either of them would be on the podium.
1993年  澳大利亚大奖赛
但从这一刻  从我站在领奖台上
But from this moment, when I am on the podium
站在他旁边的亚军位置上开始
close to him on the sub level,
他完全改变了
he has changed completely.
变成了另一个人
He was really another person,
这天之前和这天之后  完全不同
it was before this podium and after this podium.
让我无法相信
It's absolutely unbelievable,
在我看来
it was a different person,
就是另一个人  另一个车手
a different driver, in my opinion,
完全不同的性格
and a different personality.
从各方面来看  他和以前完全不同
He just behaved completely different.
在记者招待会上
At the press conference,
很有幸当时有很多记者到场
it was lucky, that we had all the TV waiting for us,
但他一直在讲  不停的讲
but he was talking and speaking
不停的问我问题
and asking questions to me all the time,
就像我们以前从没说过话一样
talking as he had never talked before.
离开莲花投奔迈凯轮是对的
It was certainly right go to McLaren after the Lotus.
绝对是个明智的选择
It was absolutely the right choice.
和阿兰·普罗斯特竞争
And to compete himself against Alain Prost
是一件非常勇敢和大胆的事情
was a very brave and very shrew thing to do.
因为他知道  或者说是坚信
Shrew because he knew, or he believed,
他比普罗斯特更强
that he was better than Prost
通过跟F1当年的标志性人物
and, by measuring him against the man
进行面对面的较量
who was accepted as the arts of Formula One at the time,
他就能向世人证明自己的实力
he could prove for good and all his own quality.
他发现  有一支车队
So he could see that that there was another team
比迈凯轮更强
that had a better car than McLaren,
拥有九十年代初最好的赛车
and the best car by mile in the early 90s.
92年  他们帮助奈杰尔·曼塞尔夺冠
You know, in the 92 they won World championship with Nigel Mansell
93年帮助普罗斯特夺冠
and in '93 they won with Prost.
他希望在94年  坐在车里的人是自己
And he wanted to be in the that car for '94.
就是这时  他的直觉背弃了他
and that was when his instincts let him down.
或许  就客观因素和种种数据而言
Probably, given the known factors and given the parameters,
这个决定没错
it was the right decision.
即使回到那个年代  面对当时的情况
and you would go back and look at the conditions
你也会做出同样的决定
and make exact the right decision.
但事实证明  这是个错误的决定
Exactly that decision, it happened to be the wrong one.
但在当时  他不可能预见未来
But there was no way he could have known that,
直到他在94年
until he actually stepped
坐进了威廉姆斯的赛车
into the Williams car for the first time in '94.
威廉姆斯车手发布会
埃尔顿一直都是最好的车手
Ayrton is always the best driver available,
是一辆车能遇到的最好的车手
the best driver in car racing.
弗兰克·威廉姆斯
所有的合作伙伴
and all partners,
投资商和赞助商都期待我们夺冠
investors and sponsors expect that of us.
不管多好的设备
and that is there for the best piece of equipment,
只要你想要
if you like,
我们都能安装到赛车上  满足要求
we can put it in that machine, to deliver to our requirement.
国际汽联宣布
The International Motor Sport Federation has banned
禁止在F1赛车上使用有争议的
some of the  controversial computer devices
车手辅助电子设备
which help drivers in Formula One motor racing.
这项禁令意在打破诸如
The ban is designed to stop domaination
威廉姆斯-雷诺等大车队
of the richest Formula One teams,
对赛事的垄断
like the Williams-Renault, the world champions.
1994年
对埃尔顿·塞纳来说
To Ayrton Senna,
唯一的对手就是时间
is a race against time.
目前的问题是团队的磨合和对新车的适应
Must be an integral team and adapt to the new car.
他说  这并不容易
He says they are not at ease.
今年的赛车不再有电子辅助系统
The car is no longer electronic components used last year:
牵引力控制
traction control
特殊刹车系统和动态悬架系统
special brakes and active suspension.
没有了动态悬架系统
The cars are much less stable
赛车的稳定性大大降低
without the electronically controlled suspension.
驾驶赛车将更困难
As a result, are more difficult to drive
更容易出现脱离赛道甚至撞车的现象
and it is very likely to occur more coats and off the track.
更多的撞车  对观众来说更有看点
More coats mean more fun for the audience
对我们来说  安全完成比赛是第一位的
and also for us, until the pilot nothing happens.
不然的话  这可不是一件好事
Otherwise, it is not a good situation.
巴西大奖赛
1994年3月27日
被第一名落下将近八秒钟
almost eight seconds between them now
56/71
威廉姆斯车队首席工程师  派翠克·哈德
我们当然不开心
things Ayrton in the car at that moment,
操控不是很好
the handling isn't particular good.
太平洋大奖赛
1994年4月17日
去年安装在赛车上的电子辅助装置
The cars weren't supposed to have any of the electronic aids
今年被禁止使用
installed the previous year.
可塞纳却坚信
But Senna became convinced
赛季前两站均获胜的
that the Benetton beed driven by Michael Schumacher
贝纳通车队车手迈克尔·舒马赫
who have won the first two races of the season
在赛车上保留了一些
have retain some of those particularly the traction control,
防止赛车打滑的牵引力控制系统
the thing that eliminated wheelspin.
声音来自
弗兰克·威廉姆斯\N威廉姆斯车队经理
伊莫拉赛道  圣马力诺大奖赛
1994年4月
如果他带着个人情绪参加了那场比赛
If he carried any emotion going to that race,
那肯定和之前的比赛不一样
that was different from previous races,
或许是因为
it would probably be the frustration
知道他的竞争对手的赛车上
to know that his principle rival is driving a car
安装了违禁设备而感到沮丧
with a illegal system on it.
对手无视公平竞赛的做法激怒了他
And that would always incense his sense of fair play.
我认为
I would put anything,
他的任何异常举动
anything that was abnormal on his behaviour,
都是由这一点引起的
just down to that knowledge and believe.
我必须说  这是他当时说的
I must say what he said,
因为我自己也没法确定
because I can not judge myself
但他当时确信  贝纳通在作弊
but he was convinced Benetton was cheating.
这个问题使得他非常失落  非常困扰
He was very upset and he was in big trouble because of that.
又一次  他开始抱怨赛车
and again not pretty happy with the car,
抱怨赛车的表现
with the performance of the car.
很显然  他很不开心
So, he was obvious not happy,
他说他已经失去了动力
saying that he could not find the motivation.
他对我说过很多次
Many times he told me:
我不想再跟迈克尔比下去了
"I can not be motivated against Michael,
不想跟任何人比了
against all other drivers."
就像
It was really like
他失去了激情一样
if he had lost his passion,
对赛车不满意  对车队不满意
he had problems with the car, problem with the team,
安全问题  或许是一些个人问题
safety, maybe some small personal problems, possible.
但他丧失了他的车技
But he had lost his skill.
非常出乎意料
That was very surprising.
在我看来  很显然
It was very apparent to me,
包括埃尔顿身边的几个人
and to several other people around Ayrton.
他的教练  也是最好的朋友  约瑟夫
Josef, his trainer and probably one of his closest friends,
席德·沃特金斯
Sid Watkins,
我们三个人  由于不同的原因
all three for this, for different reasons,
很快达成了共识
very quickly formed an opinion
埃尔顿后悔离开了迈凯轮
that Ayrton quickly regretted leaving the team.
倒不是因为竞争的问题
Not specifically because of competitiveness or uncompetitiveness,
更像是因为
but more because he didn't
他没想到现在的车队文化
expect find himself in such a different culture
和原来的车队有那么大的差别
and one which is quite alien to the way he was.
塞纳  夺冠的责任
我们现在从零开始
We are here starting from zero.
所以也可以说  冠军之路从这里开始
so basically our championship starts here.
条件不是很好  但这就是现实
It's not the comfortable position to be in, but that's the reality.
你已经在这里赢了三次了
You've won here three times already,
你还那么想赢第四次吗
are you really do need to make it four?
我很希望
I would love to.
1994年4月29日  星期五  练习赛
那个周末塞纳太紧张了
Senna was so nervous that weekend.
我没见过他紧张成这样
I had never seen him so tense.
我没见他笑过一下
I never saw him smile even for a moment.
一直保持着精神高度集中
Always maintained a concentrated expression,
生气而又伤心的表情
irritated, sad.
是平衡的问题
It is the balance.
很不稳定
It is unstable.
车况更差了
The car has worsened.
是持续偏向一侧
is it generally more one balance than the other,
还是两侧交替
or it's changing?
转向不足更严重了
It tends to understeer more.
第一圈  转向不足
In the first lap, tended to understeer.
第二圈  突然就变了
Then, in the second lap, has changed abruptly.
转向过度和转向不足吗
Oversteer and understeer?
对的
Yes
车子不是在转弯的中线
Instead of in the mid of the corner,
而是完全偏离
it goes straight away.
当抓地力应该减小时会过了头
When it's supposed to break away, it breaks away even more.
他的车子就像是
He was getting into a car that was like a kind of,
未驯服的小马
you know, an unbroken colt if you like.
他有很多问题和缺点
He had a lot of problems, a lot of vices
需要下功夫去解决
that needed to be worked on and ironed out.
有些还是根本问题
Some of them seemed pretty fundamental.
车手最痛恨的事情
One things that the driver hates above all else
就是车子在转弯时不听话
is a car that changes its behaviour in the middle of a corner.
有两种情况  转向过度和转向不足
There are two things, oversteer and understeer.
我们以前称转向过度为四轮漂移
Oversteer is what we used to call the four-wheel drift.
当你踩着油门转向时
You know, when you steer a car with throttle
你要转方向盘来平衡
and you turn the steering wheel to balance it
就好像要驶向你实际要去的
in such a way that you appear to be going in an opposite direction
相反方向
the way you want to go.
但实际上车子滑行过了转角
But actually the car drifts around... slides around the corner.
转弯不足是指你需要比预期的
Understeer is when you have to put more steer on than you expect
转向更多才能驶过转弯处
to get around a corner.
大部分车
And the worst thing is most cars
只有其中的一样
have the character sick of one or the other
但非常差的车会两样都有
but really bad cars have both.
在转弯时
And they change from one to the other in the blink of an eye
瞬间相互变化
in the middle of a corner
在你最不希望它发生的时候
when you least wanting that to happen.
这点让车手非常不安
And that's very very disturbing for driver,
因为这会摧毁他对于车子的信心
because it destroys his faith in the integrity of the car.
而车手对于车子的特征和行为
And that's absolutely crucial to particularly Formula One,
建立起完全的信任是非常重要的
to developing, for the driver, to develop that complete trust
尤其是对于F1而言
in the car's temperament and behaviour.
在94年的赛季一开始
And it was very clear in the beginning of 94 season
威廉姆斯车队很明显缺乏这点
that Williams absolutely didn't have that.
他车子的平衡
He had this really unpleasant characters
不断地改变
to give change in its balance.
这问题需要花很大力气去解决
And that takes a lot of sorting out.
在赛季末尾  我们看到
You know, we saw, by the end of the season,
威廉姆斯确实解决了这个问题
that Williams had sorted it out.
达蒙·希尔不断赢得比赛  接近问鼎冠军
Damon Hill was winning races, challenging for the title.
而且在后面的三个赛季
And for the next season and the two seasons after that,
96和97赛季  威廉姆斯车队赢得了冠军
in '96 and '97, Williams won the title again
因为他们已经走过了那段低谷
because they had gone through that bad period.
但塞纳正好在这个时候加入
But Senna's arrival coincided with it.
我觉得那让他很是困扰
and I think that was very - that was very disturbing to him,
因为这和他的预期不符
because he'd gone there, expecting something else.
他期待的是加入后
He'd gone there expecting to be able to
能开着一辆可以赢得比赛的车
walk into a championship winning car.
而相反  他却需要认真地
Instead what he found with himself was a serious job
帮助工程师们
of helping the engineers
排除车子的问题从而使之再次具有竞争力
to purge the car of its vices and make it competitive again.
鲁本斯·巴里切罗
乔丹车队
不用  我认识
No, I already know.
是因为久仰大名还是你们以前见过
The familiar name of or you've already met?
我认识他是因为我关注F1  而且我们见过
I know him because I follow Formula One and we met.
那你怎么还这么紧张
Why are you so nervous, then?
因为站在他这样的人旁边
Because standing next to someone like him
总是让我很紧张
always put me in turmoil.
祝你接下来比赛好运
Good luck to the sample and the eventual champion.
鲁本斯·巴里切罗
排位赛
该死的
Damn.
你见到鲁本斯了吗
Have you seen Rubens?
他还好  他还好
He's alright. He's alright.
当然他受了些惊吓  但是他还好
He's shocked of course, but he's alright.
-你跟他说过话了吗  -说了
- Have you talked to him?  - Yes.
鲁本斯  早日康复
Get well, Rubens.
1994年4月30日  星期六
当我到伊莫拉赛道时
When I arrived at Imola
第一个看到的就是大屏幕
and the first thing I saw was the screen
上面写着  阿兰  我们想你了
where it has recorded "Alain, we miss you."
我们想念你  阿兰
"We miss you, Alain."
我的朋友阿兰  我们想你了
"To my friend, Alain. We miss you."
或者我想你了
or "I miss you."
我很开心
I'm very very happy.
这是他为我做的最棒的事情
Honestly, it's maybe the best thing he has done to me.
因为这对我很重要
Because this message is very important,
不止因为  很不幸地
not only because that happened, unfortunately,
这是他死前一天的事
the day before he died.
如果你
When you are...
从一个车手的角度出发
Try to put yourself in a driver's position.
这时候你再想想
When you do that...
为什么埃尔顿会在那时候想到我
Why Ayrton would think about myself at this time of the day.
我总是思考这个问题  真是难以置信
I always thought about that. It is unbelievable to me.
这个表达出了很强烈的信息
And this message is very strong.
而这对我一直很重要
And it has been something really important to me.
声音来自
约翰·比西尼亚诺\NESPN评论员
也对新车很不适应
And he was very uncomfortable with the car.
但他还是努力争得了杆位
But he struggled and put it on pole position.
该死的
Damn.
我得控制我自己
I must regain control of myself.
罗兰·拉岑博格
塞米特克车队
我在车上花的功夫
I do things with the car that no one ...
放松一点  好吧
Just swing it around a bit, yeah?
罗兰·拉岑博格
塞米特克车队
320公里每小时
320km/h.
伊莫拉赛道新闻中心
32号车的车手
that the driver of car 32,
MTV-塞米特克-福特车队罗兰·拉岑博格
MTV Simtek Ford, Roland Ratzenberger
在4月30日星期六
succumbed to an injury sustained in the accident
伊莫拉赛道排位赛练习的
which took place in the Imola Circuit
事故中受伤身亡
during Saturday's qualifying practice April 30th.
这是我们第一次面对
It was the first time that we've
同一代的车手去世
faced with the death of a driver of our generation.
那个下午的气氛非常沉重
The atmosphere is very heavy that afternoon.
每个人都在思考  我们在做什么
Everybody were thinking about what are we doing here.
做这些的意义是什么
Or what's the point.
埃尔顿那天非常沮丧而且落了泪
Ayrton was very very upset and cried that day.
我跟他说
And that's when I said to him
埃尔顿  你已经赢得过
"You know, Ayrton, you've already been
三次世界冠军了
three times the world champion.
你是世界上速度最快的人
You're the fastest man in the world."
他喜欢钓鱼  所以我说
And he liked fishing. So I said "Why don't you quit,
不如我们一起退役  然后去钓鱼
and I'll quit. And we'll just go fishing."
他说  席德  我不能退役
He said, "Sid, I can't quit."
严禁进入
那个星期六晚餐时
That Saturday, at dinner,
弗兰克·威廉姆斯完全不确定
Frank Williams was not at all sure
塞纳会不会出赛
Senna would be presented at the start.
我确定我不想比赛
I was sure that I did not want to compete.
我最后一次见到埃尔顿是那个周日
The last time I saw Ayrton was that Sunday.
他非常焦虑不安
He was very agitated.
一些朋友跟他谈话
Some friends went to talk to him.
他非常焦躁
He was very agitated,
在赛场上走来走去
was coming from Williams to the box, back and forth.
在他们走进赛车之前
Before they take print position in the cabin,
我总是问问他们的策略
I always ask something about the strategy.
问巴西的车手或者其他附近的车手
Brazilian pilots and others who are near,
有的人回答了我  有的人没有
some of them respond, others do not.
但通常他们都会跟我说些
But they always say the important things
我能在比赛中跟观众讲讲的事情
I can report to the public during the race.
我以为我也能问埃尔顿些问题
I expected to be able to
但我没问成
give my question to Ayrton, but could not.
我发觉那不是个提出这种要求的好时机
I realised that was not the time for such an application.
1994年5月1日  星期日
声音来自
维维安·塞纳\N埃尔顿的姐姐
于是他翻开圣经  读了一段
He opened the Bible and read a passage that said
那段说  上帝会赐予最好的礼物
that God would give the greatest gift of all,
或是上帝他自己
or God himself.
撞车了
A collision.
周围的车都绕过去了  看
All pass around. Look.
重放
JJ·莱赫托
贝纳通车队
严重的撞车  雷梅和莱赫托运气很不好
A nasty collision. Lamy and Lehto have had no luck.
佩德罗·雷梅
莲花车队
安全车进入了
Enter the safety car. Safety car
据说埃尔顿在赛前透露
They told me that Ayrton had revealed to someone before the race
他带着奥地利国旗
of holding or carrying a flag of Austria.
如果他能夺冠  或者站上颁奖台
In victory, or if he was still on the podium, very likely,
希望能挥动这国旗向罗兰·拉岑博格致敬
wanted to wave it as a tribute to Roland Ratzenberger.
安全车车灯熄灭了
Lights out the safety car.
这说明安全车要驶入维修区了
It means that the safety car is about to come into the pits.
比赛重新开始  塞纳领先
Starting over. Senna is in the lead.
舒马赫位居第二
Schumacher is second.
第六圈  迈克尔·舒马赫
On the sixth lap, Michael Schumacher
试图对塞纳施加压力
trying to put pressure on the Senna.
埃尔顿·塞纳车载摄像机
6/58
塞纳撞车了
Senna crashed,
在坦布罗莱弯
at the Tamburello curve.
非常严重的事故
A very serious accident.
声音来自
席德·沃特金斯教授\NF1赛医
通过他的神经精神体征
And I saw from his neurological signs,
我能看出这是致命的头部伤
that it was going to be a fatal head injury.
然后他叹了口气  接着身体就放松了
Then he sighed, and his body relaxed.
就在那时  虽然我不信教
And that was the moment ... I am not religious,
但我觉得就在那时他的灵魂离开了
but I thought that his spirit had departed.
看着直升机飞向医院
Seeing the helicopter going to the hospital,
我还在心存希望
I was still hoping.
我没发觉
I did not realise...
在现场解说时我并没发觉
During the live commentary I did not realise.
我猜测他肯定是受伤严重
I imagined that he was going to be hurt
他的状况会很不好
and he was going to be live in a bad shape.
但我没有意识到他去世了
but I did not realise he was dead.
也许是我不想意识到这点
I did not want to realise, probably.
那是不现实的
It was unreal.
埃尔顿的事故是由他自己的车子引起的
Ayrton's accident was caused by problems of his own car.
这起事故
And, certainly where,
与他和周围其他赛车的竞赛
in no way connected to the competitiveness
绝无关联
of any of the cars around him.
总有人会说
Again there are people who would claim
贝纳通车队的迈克尔
that he was pursued of Michael in the Benetton was
追得过紧  因为他需要弥补
overly aggressively, because of his necessity to compensate
车子本身的不足
for the inadequacies of his car.
但我觉得那根本就是胡说
But again, I think that's a nonsense.
这不过是那些人想要歪曲事实
It's again, it's just people trying to rewrite the script.
单纯的事实就是
Simple fact is...
几乎可以肯定的是埃尔顿死于
Ayrton almost certainly suffered a car failure,
赛车故障引起的事故
which caused the accident,
这只是一连串发生的事中的一件
it was one of those things, these things happen.
这肯定是机械故障
It was certainly a mechanical problem.
我说话很注意
I'm very careful about what I say,
因为他们改动了驾驶杆
because they made the steering column different.
不排除这种可能
It could be a possibility.
我真的不知道
I have no idea, precisely.
但肯定是机械故障
But for sure it was a mechanical failure.
不能浪费他的天赋
The gift that he has had to be used.
上天赐予他天赋  他有责任利用他的天赋
And an obligation to whatever force or power giving him that gift,
去成就事业  实现梦想
had an obligation to pursue his career, pursue his passion.
当然  这些想法
and, of course that, those thoughts
当他去世时
there were very much with me
萦绕在我脑海中
when he lost his life,
在那时  即使大家都还不确定
because even in the moment when realised,
但还是能意识到
when nobody knew for sure, but even in the moments
他真的去世了
he did lost his life,
我明白这一切都是无可避免的
I found myself strangely uncomfortable with the fact
这让我感到很不舒服
they would not have done anything different.
这是他的选择
It was what he wanted to do.
如果这是他职业生涯的
And if that was the outcome
最终归宿
linked to his career,
就算他知道  我也不觉得他会做什么改变
I do not think it would change, even if he had known it.
比赛结束时
We found that this was
我们发现事情很严重
a serious just at the end of race.
即使你得到了一些不同的消息
or even you always have some different messages.
我记得那时有人报导
I remember that we had someone people come into the commentary,
说他手臂受伤了而已
and said he had broken arm. And that's it.
大概五分钟后  我们得知了噩耗
Maybe five minutes later we had very bad news.
我说在得知事实真相前
I remember saying it was no point to say
发表声明是没有意义的
unless we knew exactly what has happened.
而我们也确实从报导中得知了消息
And we did know during the commentary.
随之而来的是大量的谣言
Then we had big rumours as always.
在去机场的路上
And on the way to the airport,
我们意识到事态的严重性
we understood it was very bad.
赛后你去见弗兰克了吗
You went to Frank after the race?
没有  我去了  抱歉
No. Actually, yes, sorry.
我赛后就去停车房找弗兰克
I went to see Frank in the garage just after the race.
是实况报导结束后我做的第一件事
It was the first thing I did after the commentary.
弗兰克和派翠克在一起
Frank and Patrick were together,
但当时他们还不知道发生了什么
but still did not know.
那时比赛刚刚结束
That was just after the race.
他们一无所知
They didn't know exactly what happenned.
他们很震惊
They were shocked,
但拒绝发表意见并默默等待
but again they didn't want to make any speculations.
我们只知道  在去机场的路上
We only knew from the track to the airport,
事情越来越严重
the seriousness of the thing was increased.
回想生命中的困难  极端情绪
Reflect on the difficult things in your life, extreme emotions,
无可避免的事情并没有好转
inevitably things do not get better,
我更加伤心难过
through thought, indeed, the pain is rising for me,
在我去巴西参加他葬礼时
my emotions then were small fractions that I had
我心都碎了
when I went to Brazil for his funeral.
在巴西人民心中
For all those people in Brazil,
对世界各地的粉丝而言
for all his fans around the world,
他会永远年轻
he will always be young.
埃尔顿·塞纳永远是那么快
Ayrton Senna will always be fast.
他不会老去
He'll never be old.
对于巴西乃至全世界而言
He will always be the champion
他永远是冠军
for Brazil and the world.
即使今时今日  这份悲痛
The grief, even today,
也许是我对他的作为做出的最伟大的阐述
maybe the greatest statement I can make about what he did.
当我遇见一个巴西人时
When I meet a Brazilian
当我说出我认识埃尔顿·塞纳
soon after that I have to say
并采访过他一百多次后
I knew Ayrton Senna and I interviewed him over 100 times.
我和我妻子  和33名巴西人
I was on a cruise in the Nile river
同在尼罗河的一艘游轮上
with 33 Brazilians on this cruise with my wife and I,
我对其中一个说
and I told one of them that
我采访过埃尔顿·塞纳一百多次
I interviewed Ayrton Senna 100 times.
接下来的一周里
Sometime during the next week,
每个巴西人都跑来找我
everyone of those Brazilians had to come to me.
他们要和与埃尔顿·塞纳
They had to talk to someone
说过话的人交谈
who had talked to Ayrton Senna.
甚至是接触与埃尔顿·塞纳
Even had to touch someone who had touched
握过手的人
who had shaken hands with Ayrton Senna.
就好像我认识的是上帝
It was like I had known, and talk to,
和我交谈  握手的那个人是神一般
touched and shaken hands with God
他们通过我  也做触碰到了神
and they had to do the same through me.
当埃尔顿赢得桂冠时
These people were about 8 or 10 years old
这些人只是8岁10岁大的孩子
when Ayrton won his championships.
作为孩子  他们被教导
And as children they were taught
这个男人是最优秀的
that this was one of the greatest man lived,
巴西人
with a Brazilian passport.
当你为这项运动付出15年时
When you dedicate fifteen years to this sport,
你会想这么做是否明智
you wonder did you spend those years wisely.
我觉得很明智
I think I did.
我了解埃尔顿·塞纳
And I know Ayrton Senna...
我相信他也是这么认为的
And I know that Ayrton Senna though he had.
你能想象吗  我很想看到
Can you imagine? I would love to see
埃尔顿带着他的子孙们在海滩上玩耍
Ayrton with children and grandchildren on the beach.
但你能想象
But you can imagine to hear a news report:
听到这么一则新闻报导吗
"Ayrton Senna dying of cancer
塞纳与癌症斗争多年后去世  享年50岁
after a long battle at the age of 50? "
我不知道  从某种浪漫而不公平的角度
I do not know. In some poetic,
在赛车中结束生命
unjust way, it was almost fitting
对他来说比较好
that he died in a race car.
即使速度很快  你也不该在
Even in a racing speed, Tamburello is not a corner
塔姆布雷罗弯道发生意外
that you would make a mistake on.
那车肯定哪里出了问题
Something on that car would have to go wrong.
可能是动力转向装置出了问题
Maybe the power steering failed.
也可能是轮胎温度过高
Maybe it was the tire temperatures that
导致赛车冲出了赛道
made the car skate straight off the road.
永远无从得知真相
It will always be a mystery.
有人提起诉讼
There was a lawsuit.
在我看来  驾驶杆失灵
In my opinion, broke the steering column
会导致赛车失去控制
and the car became uncontrollable.
但毕竟  这是起事故
But above all, it was a fatality,
因为赛车撞上围栏的角度
because the car crashed with an angle for the suspension
正好使悬挂装置击中他的头盔
went to hit his helmet.
埃尔顿不走运
Ayrton ran out of luck.
他没有骨折
He did not have a broken bone in his body.
也没有任何瘀伤
He did not have any bruising.
如果那一部分碎片
If that piece of assembly
撞击部位高6英寸或低6英寸
would have gone 6 inch higher or 6 inch lower,
他就能活下来了
he would have walked back to the paddock.
意大利  博洛尼亚市
我很幸运的
I was lucky to arrive
比他的飞机早到机场半小时
at airport half an hour before his plane arrived.
我看见灵柩被抬到消防车上
I saw the coffin put onto a fire engine,
从机场出发前往市里
and taken on the road into the city from the airport,
在一条六车道还是八车道的公路上
on a six-or eight-lane highway
所有的车辆都跟着消防车
where all the traffic was going in one direction,
向着同一个方向前进
following the fire engine.
各种你想的到的车辆
Vehicles of every kind you could possibly imaginable.
太惊人了
It was just extraordinary.
全都跟着他  挂着旗帜  拉着横幅
All followed him, many with flags, banners
在各种你想的到的车的门上
or portraits taped onto sides of cars, trucks
贴着海报
or every kind of vehicle you could imange,
在去市里的高速公路上
on this high speed road into the city,
沿路的房子窗口挤满了人
passed houses and windows filled with people,
挂着旗子横幅的公寓
apartment with flags, banners
天桥上也站满了人
overbridges crowded with people,
大家都来向他致敬
all came to salute him.
人们排队来悼念他
Then people queueing to pay homage to the body,
排七八个小时的队
people queueing for seven or eight hours.
儿童  老人  形形色色的人们
Children, old people, every kind of person,
大部分是年轻人
with a predominance of young people
人口统计显示巴西是个年轻的国家
because Brazil is a young country demographically,
而且年轻人和他
And young people seemed to
似乎有种特殊的联系
have a special relationship with him.
但也有老年人  各种各样的人
But old people as well, all kinds of people.
排几个小时的队
Queueing for hours, hours and hours
就为了瞻仰遗容
just to go pass the body
并在灵柩旁放下一些纪念品
and to leave little keepsakes by the coffin.
壮观的景象
An amazing sight.
去墓地举行葬礼的路上
And then there was another procession
又是长长的队伍
to the cemetery for the funeral.
人们攀在墙上  爬到树上
Again with people hanging every walls, trees
所有可以站立的地方都布满了人群
and any conceivable surface.
直升机在空中盘旋
The sky was filled with helicopters,
直升机之类的
use helicopters and kinds of thing.
相当于英国皇家空军的
Jets from the Brazilian Air Force,
巴西空军驾驶喷气机
the equivalent to the Red Arrows,
在空中用烟雾描绘出了塞纳的"S"
drawing "S" Of the Senna with smoke in the sky.
令人赞叹
Amazing.
我也曾参加过鲍勃·马利的葬礼
I went to the funeral of Bob Marley,
两者惊人的相似
which was very very similar
就像整个国家的人们
like the entire---entire nation coming out
都来感谢他们
to acknowledge someone
向全世界展示了他们的祖国
who represented them to the world.
1994年5月4日  巴西  圣保罗
他是我的偶像  是巴西的骄傲
He was my idol. He represented the best of Brazil.
塞纳  我想念你
I miss you, Senna.
我永远不会忘记你
Do not forget you.
巴西人民需要食物  教育  医疗保障
The Brazilians need food, education, health care
还有小小的快乐
and a little joy.
现在这点快乐也失去了
The joy it has been removed.
埃尔顿·塞纳·达·席尔瓦
没有什么可以让我远离上帝的爱
谁是你与之较量过
Who is or has been the drivers
满怀敬意的赛车手
you've competed against with greater satisfaction?
包括曾经的和现在的
Past or present.
那要退回到
I would have to go back
1978年  1979年
to 1978, 1979
1980年的时候  我开卡丁车
1980, when I was in go-kart driving.
我第一次离开巴西去欧洲比赛
I came to Europe for the first time to compete outside Brazil
作为富尔顿的队友参加比赛
as a teammate for Fullerton.
他叫富尔顿  经验丰富
His name was Fullerton. He was very experienced.
我很高兴能和他一起比赛
I enjoyed very much driving with him
因为他很快  状态稳定
because he was fast and he was consistent.
他对于我而言是个真正的赛车手
He was for me a complete driver.
就是纯粹的驾驶  纯粹的赛车
It was pure driving, pure racing.
没有政治因素
There was not any politics.
也没有金钱交易
No money invovled either.
就是纯粹的比赛
It was real racing.
那是很美好的回忆
I have that very good memory.
埃尔顿·塞纳去世时34岁
Ayrton Senna died at the age of 34.
在他死后
After his death,
国际汽联授权席德·沃特金斯教授和他的朋友
FIA mandated Professor Sid Watkins and his friend,
提高F1比赛的安全性
to improve safety in Formula One.
自那之后  F1赛场上没有出过致死事故
Since then, it was not registered no death in Formula One.
埃尔顿·塞纳基金会
The Ayrton Senna Foundation,
由他的姐姐维维安于1995年创办
created in 1995 by his sister Viviane,
为贫困的巴西儿童
which has contributed more than 12 million
阿兰·普罗斯特是董事之一
One director is Alain Prost.
捐助超过1200万
to poor Brazilian children.